<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Deaths deliverance, and Eliahes fiery charet, or The holy mans triumph after death Delivered in two sermons preached at Plymouth, the one the 16. the other the 19. of August: the former at the funerall of Thomas Sherwill, an eminent and pious magistrate of that place. 1631. By Alexander Grosse now pastor of Bridford.</title>
            <author>Grosse, Alexander, 1596?-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117896</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853105</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18473</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18473)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1239:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Deaths deliverance, and Eliahes fiery charet, or The holy mans triumph after death Delivered in two sermons preached at Plymouth, the one the 16. the other the 19. of August: the former at the funerall of Thomas Sherwill, an eminent and pious magistrate of that place. 1631. By Alexander Grosse now pastor of Bridford.</title>
                  <author>Grosse, Alexander, 1596?-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 32, 34-40, [1], 3, 2-62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Paine, for Francis Eaglesfield, and are to be sold at the Marygold in Saint Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The second sermon, "Eliahs fiery chariot or The holy mans triumph after death .. A sermon preached .. at the funerall of .. Matthias Nicols" has separate dated title page and pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherwill, Thomas, d. 1631.</term>
               <term>Nicols, Matthias, d. 1631.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18473:1"/>
            <p>DEATHS DELIVERANCE, AND ELIAHES <hi>FIERY CHARET,</hi> OR The Holy mans Triumph after Death.</p>
            <p>Delivered in two Sermons prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at PLYMOVTH, the one the 16. the other the 19. of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> the former at the Funerall of <hi>Thomas Sherwill,</hi> an Eminent and pious Magiſtrate of that place. 1631.</p>
            <p>By ALEXANDER GROSSE now Paſtor of <hi>Bridford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 37.37.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Marke the perfect man, and behold the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right; for the end of that man is peace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Paine,</hi> for <hi>Francis Eaglesfield,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Mary-gold</hi> in Saint <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18473:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18473:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVL IOHN WADDON Maior of <hi>Plim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> and the reſidue of that famous Corporation, the bleſſed increaſe of all Grace on earth, and the fulneſſe of all Glory in Heaven.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull, and much reſpected,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an Axiome among the <hi>Logicians: Quicquid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur, recipitur ad mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum recipientis:</hi> and ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, wee are taught by dayly experience, that the welfare and iſſue of our actions is much dependant upon other mens inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations: ſometimes groundleſſe ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, cauſeleſſe jealouſies of mens intentions, ends, and purpoſes, doe put an evill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb facs="tcp:18473:3"/> upon a very good and holy under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and turne the ſweeteſt flower into a loathſome, and unſavory weede: thus <hi>Davids</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 10.3.4.5.</note> ſervants ſent by him in kindnes, to viſit and comfort <hi>Hanun</hi> after the death of his father, were upon a groundleſſe jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie entertained as ſpies, and not as friends, ſent away not with thankes, but with diſgrace; having their garments cut off to the buttockes, and their beards ſhaved off to the halfe. Sometimes the low eſtate and condition of the Agent, doth much obſcure and darken the glory of the worke; thus <hi>Salomon</hi> tells us,<note n="b" place="margin">Eccle. 9.15.</note> 
               <hi>there was a little City, and few men in it; and there came a great King againſt it, and beſieged it, and built great bulwarkes againſt it; now there was found in it a poore wiſe man, and he by his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome delivered the City, yet no man remembred that ſame poore man:</hi> the jewell is deſpiſed becauſe the Casket is not rich and gilded; &amp; thence it was that they looked on our Saviour, as on a<note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 53.2.</note> dry tree, as on one that had no beauty for which they ſhould deſire him; called into<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 13.54, 55, 56, 57.</note> queſtion his learning, tooke offence at him, becauſe as man, he had (as they conceived) a poore
<pb facs="tcp:18473:3"/> originall; ſometimes a prejudicate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, a foreſtalled opinion; this maketh men with<note n="e" place="margin">Iohn. 1.46.</note> 
               <hi>Nathaniel</hi> to queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any good can come out <hi>Nazareth.</hi> Sometimes want of Complement, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane varniſhings, to ſet forth the worke; the cloath is not regarded, becauſe the lace wanteth: Thus <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching ſeemed<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.</note> fooliſh to the <hi>Grecians,</hi> becauſe it wanted the inticing words of mans wiſedome. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intentions, good and profitable underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, have many clouds to darken them, many tongues of a vicious and different temper to gloſſe upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them: But for mine own part (the integrity of mine intentions war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranting to mine own heart this enterprize) I am reſolved with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to take it a ſmall thing to be judged of<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.3.</note> mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If I may do any good, give any light, miniſter any comfort, though but to one poore ſoule, by my weake and deſpiſed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, I feare not, I regard not a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand cenſures. It is not the importunitie of others, the commemoration of paſt kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, expectation of, or invention unto future favours, but the love I beare to the parties deceaſed, my deſire to have their
<pb facs="tcp:18473:4"/> memoriall preſerved, continued; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of your memories with the bleſsing ye enjoyed by their life, and the loſſe ye ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by their death; the quickning of you to an holy converſation, the preparing of you for your own diſſolution, are the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving cauſes of the publication of theſe two Sermons.</p>
            <p>It is not earthly honour, worldly fulneſſe, fleſhly pleaſures, vaniſhing greatneſſe, tranſitory abundance, that is the richeſt jewell, the brighteſt Sunne, the ſweeteſt muſicke, the moſt honorable Crowne; all theſe are ſand ſinking, exhalations vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, thornes pricking, Eagles flying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,<note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 23.5</note> 
               <hi>things which are not.</hi> Theſe are often given for a ſnare, as <hi>Sauls</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 18 21.</note> daughter to <hi>David;</hi> Theſe like<note n="k" place="margin">Judg. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>Dalilah</hi> betray us, after they have ſung ſweetly to us, cut off our lockes, ſpoyle us of what ſhould make us happie, and involve us in an irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable miſerie: like<note n="l" place="margin">Iudg. 4.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Iael,</hi> after they have fed us, cloathed us, and in our imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſecured us, drive the naile of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into our temples: like <hi>Abſaloms</hi> feaſt for<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 13.28.</note> 
               <hi>Amnon,</hi> they doe but prepare us for deſtruction. To a ſoule ſavingly enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb facs="tcp:18473:4"/> unfainedly humbled, truely ſanctified, throughly affected with the taſte of Gods goodneſſe, bleſſedly enriched with ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and heavenly graces, beautified and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned with the precious pearle ſurpaſsing all earthly merchandiſe: what theſe things are let <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpeake;<note place="margin">Greg. in <hi>1</hi> Reg. cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitiae pereuntes, &amp; tranſitoriae faculta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, niſi ſtercora, aeterna diligentibus?</hi> what are periſhing riches, and tranſitorie abilities, but dung to them that love eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie? And thus <hi>Paul</hi> accounted all to be but<note n="n" place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>dung and droſſe in compariſon of the knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> It is not greatneſſe, but goodneſſe; not worldly riches, but heavenly graces; not the higheſt top of earthly felicities, but true holineſſe, is the way leading to the Crowne, and joy of never failing continuance. Though (as one ſaith) the purſuite of purity is deemed the height of folly; yet you ſhall find this infallibly, conſtantly, unchangeably true; That true godlineſſe, the religious exerciſe of holy duties, heavenly walking with God, is a pillar of the greateſt ſtrength to ſupport, a ſtarre of the brighteſt light to direct, a jewell of the richeſt price to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich,
<pb facs="tcp:18473:5"/> a flower of the moſt orient and ſhining beauty to adorne, and a ſhield of the moſt tryed metall to defend any Kingdome, towne, family, people or particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Many bee the inſtruments and meanes which God of his goodneſſe hath ordained, prepared, ſanctified, for the begetting, breeding, nouriſhing, eſtabliſhing, and perfecting of this godlineſſe, this religion in the hearts of his people: among the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, theſe two, the Miniſterie of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, meditation upon our uncertaine, yet ſpeedy diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are not the leaſt effectual, preualent, and powerfull, to make us ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, carefull, and circumſpect runners in this race, and to forward us in this holy and bleſſed worke. Therefore as the<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note> Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles gather themſelves to the Carkaſſe, as the<note n="p" place="margin">Mica. 4.1, 2.</note> waters flow to the Ocean, as the<note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 5.4.5.</note> lame men came to <hi>Betheſda,</hi> as the Queene of the South came from farre to heare the wiſedom of <hi>Salomon;</hi> ſo come ye, attend, wait upon, reverence, receive, embrace and love the holy and faithfull Miniſtrie of the VVord. Here is the ſweeteſt muſick that ever eare heard, the delicat'ſt Feaſt
<pb facs="tcp:18473:5"/> that ever palate taſted, the moſt comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tidings that ever man brought, the moſt glorious light that ever eye did ſee: here is a garden which hath a flower for every ſanctified noſtrill; an Artillerie-houſe, wherein are weapons for every ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier fighting Gods battell; an <hi>Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries</hi> ſhoppe that hath a healing medicine for every wounded ſoule; here is a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor for every circumciſed eare, a guide for every traveller, a comforter for every ſorrowfull and dejected ſpirit. This is the inſtrumentall ſtaffe and ſtay of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; the Crowne and glory of the Lords people. But as our Saviour tooke occaſion, from the quality of the perſons receiving the Goſpel, to ſay,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 11.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>the poore receive the Goſpel, and bleſſed is hee that is not offended in me;</hi> So may I take occaſion from the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the perſons preaching, and from their manner of teaching to ſay,<note n="t" place="margin">Eſay 11.6. Pſal. 8.2 2 Cor. 10.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> mortal men, weake men, men of low eſtate and condition, men whoſe bodily preſence is weake, and ſpeech contemptible, preach the Goſpel, and that in a plaine manner without oſtentation: and bleſſed is he that is not offended, becauſe this Treaſure is
<pb facs="tcp:18473:6"/> brought in a wooden Veſſell, becauſe men preach not themſelves, but Chriſt; that ſo the excellency of the power may appeare to be of God, and not of men. Jt is with us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, as we are carnall, as it was with <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Livi: lib. <hi>37.</hi> Plut. in Comp. Scipio. &amp; Annib.</note> and his people, in another caſe. Hiſtory makes mention, how <hi>Antiochus</hi> prepared againſt the <hi>Romans</hi> an Army very great and huge, of men of many Nations, but white livered Souldiers, not ſo ſtrong with armour, as gliſtering with gold and ſilver: <hi>Antiochus</hi> himſelfe was amazed at the ſight of it, and thought it invincible; and ſo did the ſimple fooles of his Countrey: but the <hi>Romans</hi> contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, and <hi>Annibal</hi> jeſted at it. So na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men being to wage warre againſt their ſpirituall adverſaries, will<note n="u" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> heape up many teachers, and if their Sermons gliſter with the gold and ſilver, or rather with the gilded braſſe, and copper of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane eloquence, ſupercilious ſpeeches, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and quaint conceipts and devices, though there be little or no ſpirituall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in it; yet they ſtand amazed at it think that the battle is wonne, that the day and crowne is theirs: when it is too apparent
<pb facs="tcp:18473:6"/> that Satan, and ſinne, like <hi>Annibal</hi> and his <hi>Romans,</hi> doe ſcorne, and are no more moved, no more affrighted with it, then with the admiration uſed by the<note n="x" place="margin">Acts 19.15.</note> ſonnes of <hi>Sheva,</hi> where Satan prevailed, &amp; they ran away wounded; for as Satan ſayd to them: <hi>Paul I know, &amp; Ieſus I know, but what are ye?</hi> So in this caſe the evill ſpirit wil, at leaſt may ſay: them that preach Chriſt ſincerely, faithfully, powerfully, I know; but what are the feeble ſayings of Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Philoſophers, or the rythmes and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of fond Poets, who ſanctified theſe as a meanes to conquer ſinne and Sathan? Two things have I found, (which J pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the view and cenſure of all the Lords people) the one by internall ſenſe and feeling, the other by externall obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: the firſt is this; The more or leſſe the Miniſter of God hath of the <hi>Spirit</hi> in his preaching, ſo much the more or leſſe powerfull is his Sermon, either for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, converſion, or conſolation: The ſecond is this, That holy, humble, and faithfull Paſtors, though for humane Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence like <hi>Cicero,</hi> for their abilities in Philoſophy like <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> for their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifying
<pb facs="tcp:18473:7"/> faculty like <hi>Ovid;</hi> yet in <hi>Gods Sanctuarie</hi> have they laid aſide theſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, and ſtudied to preach God &amp; Chriſt Jeſus, not out of <hi>Homer, Virgil, Cicero, Ariſtotle,</hi> but of out the <hi>Sacred Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> with all<note n="x" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.18, 19.</note> poſsible plainneſſe, fit for mens capacities. And for mine owne part, I thinke Gods Miniſters ſhould uſe humane helpes, as <hi>Abraham</hi> did his<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 22.5.</note> Aſſe and his Servant; they may goe with them to the foot of the Hill, &amp; there ſtay, but not aſcend into the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> where they preach Chriſt Ieſus, and offer their ſpiritual ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, except in ſome<note n="z" place="margin">Act. 17.28. Tit. 1.12.</note> extraordinary caſes. For thus S. <hi>Auguſtine: In doctrina ſacrae Scripturae authoritatem debet Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus praeferre, non ſaecularium literaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peritiam oſtentare; non enim Epiſcopi eſt officium Grammaticam exponere, nec laudes Iovis perſonet os pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis:</hi> that is, the Miniſter muſt preferre the authority of ſacred Scripture in his teaching, and not ſhew forth his skill in ſecular or humane learning; it is not the dutie of a Miniſter to expound Grammer, or ſound forth the prayſes of Jupiter: this have I made hold to tell you, that you may
<pb facs="tcp:18473:7"/> not ſticke <hi>in cortice,</hi> in the naked world of a Sermon, like men that behold onely the outſide of the houſe; but open the doore, goe in, and ſee what good cheere the Spirit of God doth make there for your ſoules;<note place="margin">Origen in Levit. Hom. <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> for as <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, <hi>Spiritus divinis verbis convaleſcit, nutrimenta ſpiritus ſunt divina lectio, orationes aſſiduae, ſermo doctrinae; his alitur cibis, his convale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcit, his actor efficitur:</hi> It is not an humane but a divine word which nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and maketh the ſoule holily opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: it is Gods word which doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the underſtanding, awaken the conſcience, purifie the affection, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile to God, worke peace in the heart, and fill the inward man with all goodneſſe: thinke of theſe things, and of many poore ſoules that amongst you come within the walles of the Lords houſe, and there ſtand and ſee, but heare not, that you may accordingly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for your owne, and their everlaſting good.</p>
            <p>And as the holy, and ſoule-refreſhing Miniſterie of the Goſpell, ſo alſo the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meditation of our owne ſlippery ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb facs="tcp:18473:8"/> fleeting condition, is a ſpur very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible to quicken us in the way of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: were that of the Prophet to <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 King. 20.</note> 
               <hi>thou mayeſt not live but die,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſounding in our eares, and freſh in our memories, it would cauſe us to ſet both houſe and ſoule in order, it would cauſe us with the Merchant to buy while the Mart laſteth, with the Traveller to walke while the light ſhineth, with the Mariner to row while the tide ſerveth. And that the word of God may now be pleaſant and profitable, your death at the laſt comfortable and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; let the preſence, power, and increaſe of theſe foure inſuing graces, like foure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious jewels adorne you. <hi>1.</hi> Humilitie, which is in Gods eye a<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.3.</note> Pearle of great price, a fruit, an evidence of the<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 11.2.</note> 
               <hi>wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which is from above,</hi> the firſt<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> leſſon learned in the Schoole of Chriſt Jeſus, and that which maketh us capeable<note n="e" place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> of all graces. <hi>2.</hi> Sinceritie, let your inward diſpoſition, your outward converſation, be like our Saviours Coate without ſeame; it is your<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal 32.1, 2.</note> bleſſedneſſe, your prayſe before God and all good men now, and will be your joy and your<note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note> glory at the laſt, to bee true
<pb facs="tcp:18473:8"/> 
               <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> right <hi>Nathaniels,</hi> in whom is no guile. <hi>3.</hi> Vnitie, a holy concord, a ſweete agreement in every good way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your ſelves: this is a fruit of the higheſt<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 1. Iam. 3.17.</note> wiſedome, like a<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 13 3.1.2.</note> precious oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Gods noſtrils, a ſingular ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your mutuall converſation, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and communication, a great ſtrengthning, and a powerfull prevention of much evill. <hi>4.</hi> Conſtancy in all the waies of God, having begunne in the ſpirit, end not in the fleſh, be not weary of well doing; having put your hand to Gods plow, looke not back, but come forth as the<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 19.5.</note> Sunne, like a Bridegroome out of his Chamber, adorned with all ſpirituall ſplendor and brightneſſe; and rejoyce yee like a mighty man to runne the race of Gods Commandements:<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 40.31.</note> mount up like the Eagle, walke on, and faint not; ſo ſhall you at the laſt embrace death as a friend, reſt in your grave, as on a Bed of Downe, have your ſoules car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in a fiery Chariot into Heaven, be entertained with moſt ſweete embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by the <hi>LORD IESVS,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:18473:9"/> have with <hi>IEHOVAH</hi> bleſſed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the full fruition of endleſſe joyes in his moſt glorious <hi>Kingdome:</hi> This He unfainedly deſireth, who ever reſteth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all holy ſervices,</hi> Alexander Groſſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18473:9"/>
                  <head>DEATHS DELIVERANCE.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Iſai. 57.1, 2.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>The righteous periſheth, and no man lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to heart; and mercifull men are taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken away from the evill to come.</p>
                        <p>He ſhall enter into peace: they ſhall reſt in their beds, each one walking in his uprightneſſe.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He heavieſt afflictions are ſweet mercies to Gods Servants; their greateſt loſſe doth prove their chiefeſt gaine; as the red Sea to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> proved a<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 14.28, 29.</note> grave to their enemies, a paſſage to them from their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18473:10"/> 
                     <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage: as <hi>Sampſon</hi> had<note n="b" place="margin">Judg. 14.14.</note> honey in the Lion, ſweet out of the ſowre, meate out of the eater; ſo the Lords people have light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, joy out of heavineſſe, peace out of trouble, life out of death; the wounding arrow, the piercing ſword, that ſticks in their ſides, doth prove a launcing knife; the deadlieſt poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon a ſweet purgation; the moſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall enemy doth the labour of a kinde and loving friend; as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> burdens, fury, violence, and high hand, drove <hi>Iſrael</hi> from working in an iron fornace, from living under a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and ſlaviſh bondage: ſo ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, afflictions, ſorrowes, troubles, ſickneſſe, violent diſeaſes, and death it ſelfe, turne to the ſingular good of all that love the Lord; for if they periſh, if they dye, if they lay downe their life; oh! it is for their advantage, though others, it may be, doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it; for thus the Prophet here hath it:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The righteous periſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and mercifull men are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18473:10"/> taken away, none conſidering that the righteous is taken from the evill to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Text is to a good man, like the Travellers Inne, bed, and place of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, after his long and weariſome journey; like the Mariners haven after many violent and ſtormy Tempeſts; like the<note n="c" place="margin">Ex. 9.20</note> houſes wherein the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Cattle were preſerved from the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous haile, one day threatned, and the next day inflicted; for ſo the Prophet ſaith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The righteous is taken from the evill to come: he ſhall enter into peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds, each one walking in his uprightneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the words we may conſider;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Quis.</hi> Of whom the Prophet here ſpeaketh, of <hi>the righteous and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Quid.</hi> What he ſaith of him, <hi>he periſheth, is taken away,</hi> the latter word doth well explaine the former.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Quare.</hi> Wherefore, <hi>hee is taken away from the evill to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Quomodo.</hi> How, in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18473:11"/> 
                     <hi>he is taken away in peace,</hi> he layeth downe his life in the feare of <hi>God,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in his grave, as on a bed, till the morning of the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>Qualiter.</hi> How the ſurviving men are affected with it, <hi>they lay it not to heart, they conſider it not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe be the ſtreames flowing from this fountaine, becauſe time will not give us leave with <hi>Gideons</hi> many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands to bow downe upon our knees, and drink a full draught of theſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we ſhall be conſtrained with his 300. ſouldiers to<note n="d" place="margin">Judg. 7.6.</note> lap a little, and ſo away.</p>
                  <p>To begin therefore with the two firſt of theſe jointly; <hi>Quis</hi> and <hi>Quid, who periſheth, who is taken away, The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: Gods</hi> people are <hi>righteous</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Jo. 13.10.</note> 
                     <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choativè,</hi> as the morning, the dawning of the day is light, but hath darkneſſe mingled with it: as <hi>Lazarus</hi> came forth of his grave, he was riſen, but his<note n="f" place="margin">Jo. 11.44</note> grave-cloth bound him. So Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are riſen to a new converſation out of the grave of ſinne, but their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are yet in ſome degree remaining
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18473:11"/> in them, a great hindrance to their holy walking. 2. They are <hi>righteous</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 5.6. Pſa. 119.5.</note> 
                     <hi>affectivè,</hi> they deſire it, hunger and thirſt after it. 3. They are <hi>righteous</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Iſ. 32.15.</note> 
                     <hi>effective, righteouſneſſe</hi> is their worke, their fruit, their walke. 4. They are <hi>righteous</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.21. Rom. 4.6.</note> 
                     <hi>imputativè,</hi> and ſo they be perfectly <hi>righteous,</hi> not a part, but the whole <hi>righteouſneſse</hi> of Chriſt is impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them. They are as<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 27.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Iacob</hi> in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaus</hi> their elder brothers garment, and ſo they win the bleſſing from God, as <hi>Iacob</hi> obtained the bleſſing at the hands of his Father <hi>Iſaak.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>righteous</hi> man here is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the man which doth holy and righteous workes; that walketh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and conſcionably in the way of <hi>righteouſneſſe;</hi> whoſe exerciſe is with<note n="l" place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul, to keep a conſcience void of offence towards God, and towards man;</hi> this man <hi>periſheth,</hi> is ſmitten with the arrow of temporall death, falleth in this warre, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercifull men,</hi> or men of kindneſſe, or godlineſſe, as the word alſo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, men eaſily<note n="m" place="margin">Luk. 6.36.</note> moved to grieve at
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18473:12"/> the miſeries of others, and to ſuccour them: <hi>men mercifull,</hi> even as God is <hi>mercifull;</hi> for in <hi>mercy</hi> there is the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of pitie, and the effect of helpe and ſuccour: the men thus <hi>righteous,</hi> thus mercifull, thus qualified, are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by death, whence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>That ſuch as be moſt holy and graci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous, are ſubject to a bodily diſſolution, as well as others.</hi> The ſithe cutteth the beautifull, and ſweet ſmelling flower, as ſoon as the fearne; the Axe hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe the good tree, as well as the barren, being once laid to the root of it: ſo is death impartiall; as the Deluge<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 7.19.</note> over-flowed the meadowes, orchards, gardens, as well as the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, the moſt fruitfull, as well as the more barren parts of the earth: ſo death ſpares none. <hi>God</hi> hath<note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 9.27.</note> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, the ſentence is irrecoverable, and <hi>how</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.16.</note> 
                     <hi>dyeth the wiſeman?</hi> ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, as the foole.</hi> What is become of all the <hi>Saints</hi> that lived before us? Have they not all drunk of this cup? Have they not all runne this race?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18473:12"/> Heare what the wiſe man ſaith,<note n="q" place="margin">Eccle. 8.8.</note> 
                     <hi>There is no man</hi> (whether rich or poore, high or low, young or old, holy or unholy) <hi>that hath power over the ſpirit, to retaine the ſpirit, neither hath he power in the day of death;</hi> and <hi>there is no diſcharge in that warre, neither ſhall wickedneſſe deliver thoſe that are given to it.</hi> The proofe of this is as needleſſe, as to prove the going downe of the Sunne from our Horizon, which every eye may daily behold and ſee: neither is it ſtrange, for</p>
                  <p>There is ſome ſinne, ſome corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the beſt, there is that ſeed <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> which bringeth forth death, as the moth eates the garment, the worme in the tree makes him moulder, the leak in the ſhip letteth in the water, untill at length it ſinke: ſo ſinne where it once entreth, once taketh up his abode, death doth enſue and follow after, as the threed followeth the needle, as<note n="r" place="margin">Ruth. 1.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Ruth</hi> followed <hi>Naomi,</hi> as <hi>Ionathans</hi> Armour-bearer ſaid to him,<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.7.</note> 
                     <hi>turn thee, behold I am with thee, according to thy heart:</hi> ſo may death ſay to ſinne, for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18473:13"/> which way ſoever that turnes, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before it, death doth without faile enſue and follow<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> after it. This is the<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> wages belonging to it, the payment never faileth: as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buildings,<note n="w" place="margin">Eccl. 10.18.</note> 
                     <hi>by much ſlothfulneſſe the building decayeth, and through idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the hands the houſe droppeth through:</hi> So may I ſay of theſe our earthly Tabernacles, through our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions theſe weake buildings of our bodies doe decay, and through the ſinne which is within us, this houſe droppeth through, till at length it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to the ground, commeth to the grave; ſinne is the mother, and death the daughter,<note n="x" place="margin">Lam. 3.42, 43.</note> 
                     <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.42, 43.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>2</label> This ſutes with the preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods people, they are<note n="y" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note> Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims, this is not their<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 11.9, 14.</note> Country, now they are<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.24.</note> Travellers, and tend every day to their journies end and as <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> could not come to <hi>Canaan,</hi> but through the<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Red Sea,</hi> no more can Gods people attaine their journies end, but by death; when the priſon walls are beaten downe, then they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18473:13"/> who are kept in fetters there, may goe forth,<note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>We know</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that if our earthly houſe of this taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle were diſſolved, wee have a building of God, a houſe not made with hands, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the Heavens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This maketh them alſo in ſome ſort <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>3</label> conformable to Chriſt their head; Our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi> hath drunke of this cup, trodden this path before us, and <hi>the</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 10.24.</note> 
                     <hi>Diſciple muſt not looke to bee above his Maſter:</hi> but, as in other things, ſo in this we muſt be made like him, to this we are<note n="e" place="margin">Ro. 8.29.</note> ordained, wee muſt firſt be like him in his ſufferings, and then we ſhall be like him in his raigning.<note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.11.</note> It is a faithfull ſaying, <hi>if we be dead with him, we ſhall alſo live with him, if we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer we ſhall alſo raigne with him:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Gideon</hi> ſaid unto his Souldiers,<note n="g" place="margin">Judg. 7.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Looke on me, as yee ſee mee doe, ſo doe yee:</hi> ſo muſt we looke on our <hi>Gideon,</hi> our Chriſt, our Captaine, and doe as wee have ſeene him doe before us.</p>
                  <p>This workes the utter deſtruction <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>4</label> of ſinne in them, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> by his<note n="h" place="margin">Judg. 16.30.</note> death deſtroyed the Philiſtines his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18473:14"/> enemies, ſo the righteous by their death deſtroy their corruptions; ſinne is like a ſubtile Fox, that cannot bee taken till his holds be deſtroyed; like ivie in the wall, which cannot be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally taken away, till the ſtones be pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led aſunder: <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not be freed from the<note n="i" place="margin">
                        <hi>Exo. 14.</hi> Morte pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſionem homo lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratur, ne malum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortale eſset, ita poena ipſi in miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiam ceſſit. Nazian. Orat. <hi>38.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Egyptians,</hi> till they came to the <hi>red ſea;</hi> no more can Gods people of their ſinnes, till they come to the grave: by death doe the righteous gaine the cutting off of ſinne; and death which was a puniſhment, is turned to a mercy to all that walke upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
                  <p>But Chriſt hath dyed for them, and their ſinne is forgiven, Gods Juſtice is fully ſatisfied, how then can God bee juſt in bringing death on them? <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> Shall the principall be arreſted and caſt into priſon, when the ſurety hath formerly paid the debt for him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> Chriſt who hath paid the debt for us, was freely<note n="k" place="margin">Joh. 3.16.</note> given of God to us; given, not inſtantly to conferre upon us an actuall freedome from all evills, but in due time, after we have beene
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18473:14"/> exerciſed with variety of tryalls. God doth not onely give Chriſt, but alſo apply him unto us, and when there is a full application of Chriſt to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, then there ſhall be a compleat<note n="l" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.14.</note> redemption from all evils: and thus though Chriſt have paid the ranſome, yet God doth us no wrong, in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring us to be exerciſed with many troubles, becauſe there is not yet a full application of this ranſome; and becauſe God gave him in ſuch a way and manner to bring his choſen to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as ſeemed beſt to his own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. God promiſed <hi>Canaan</hi> to <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> but yet he led them through the <hi>red ſea</hi> before he brought them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in ſo doing, did them no wrong.</p>
                  <p>Death to the people of God is not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> evill, the curſe is taken away: Death is like <hi>Moſes</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 4.3, 4.</note> ſerpent, it may at firſt ſight make the people of God afraid, as that did him; but as <hi>Moſes</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards tooke the Serpent in his hand, and it did him no harme, ſo is death to the righteous. like a Serpent without
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18473:15"/> a ſting, like a Souldier overcome, and his weapons taken from him,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.55, 56, 57.</note> 
                     <hi>O death</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) where is thy ſting? O grave where is thy victory? the ſting of death is ſinne, the ſtrength of ſinne is the Law, but thankes be unto God, which giveth us the victory through Jeſus Christ our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Death is ordained of God to be the deſtruction of ſinne in his children; as <hi>David</hi> cut off<note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam. 17 50, 51.</note> 
                     <hi>Goliahs</hi> head with his owne ſword, ſo will God deſtroy ſin by death, which is held as a ſword in ſinnes hand.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Death is to Gods people as the <hi>red ſea</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the deſtruction of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of their ſalvation, an end of all miſeries, a paſſage to everlaſting life: ſo that Gods people have freedome from the evill, but not from the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of dying; and herein is the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull power, wiſdome, and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God very clearely ſeene, even in changing the nature of death, and making it to his people ſo uſefull, which in it ſelfe is ſo hurtfull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> Doe the godly the dye, are not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18473:15"/> the righteous exempted? muſt they taſte of this cup? It is then in vaine for the wicked, unrighteous, unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to dreame of eſcapall: As the Apoſtle ſaid in another caſe,<note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17.</note> 
                     <hi>if judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begin at the houſe of God, what ſhall bee the end of them which obey not the Goſpel of God,</hi> and as our Saviour alſo ſaid in another caſe,<note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 23.31.</note> 
                     <hi>if they doe thus to the greene tree, what will they doe to the dry?</hi> So in this caſe, if death ſeize upon, and ſpare not Gods family, the houſe-hold of faith, the holy and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,<note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 61.3.</note> trees of righteouſneſſe, Trees of Gods owne planting, as the Prophet calleth them, where then be the hopes of the prophane mans delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: If holineſſe, if being in Chriſt, in covenant with God, preſerve not the righteous, the mercifull man from death; Oh thinke not then, O profane man, that riches, honour, worldly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities will preſerve thy life, theſe be ſhields of no ſtrength to defend us from the darts of death, foundations of ſand, unable to beare us up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> like that whereon the fooliſh man built his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18473:16"/> houſe,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 7.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>Whereon when the Windes blew, and the waves beat, it fell, and great was the fall thereof:</hi> ſuch will be the end of all that build upon the ſand of earthly powers, whoſe very ſtrength is weakneſſe. It was neither the ſtrength, nor height of the tree, nor faireneſſe of the leaves, nor abundance of the fruit, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the ſhadow, could preſerve it from the ſentence of the<note n="t" place="margin">Dan. 4.12, 13, 14.</note> woe, the which <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> beheld com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe from Heaven in his viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo death (when it once commeth, when the God of Heaven ſends it) will ſhake off the leaves, break downe the branches, take away the beauty of the faireſt, the might of the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, not regard the wealth of the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, but new downe the Tree, and caſt the body into the grave.<note n="v" place="margin">Pſ. 82.6.</note> 
                     <hi>I have ſaid</hi> (ſaith the Lord of them that be moſt rich, moſt potent, moſt mighty on earth) <hi>yee are Gods, and all of you are children of the most High, but yee ſhall dye like men, and periſh like one of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18473:16"/> Princes.</hi> As the fire burnes both the ſhrub and Cedar; ſo death ſpares nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poore nor rich. The Lords wrath will ſeaze upon all the wicked alike, as the<note n="w" place="margin">Iſ. 5.24.</note> 
                     <hi>the fire devoureth the ſtubble, &amp; the flame conſumeth the chaffe, ſo their root ſhall be rottenneſſe, and their bloſſome ſhall goe up as duſt, becauſe they have caſt away the Law of the Lord of Hoaſts:</hi> and woefull, miſerable and wretched will their death be. For</p>
                  <p>It ſhall end all their joyes, then <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> their<note n="x" place="margin">Job 18.5, 6.</note> Candle will be put out, as the<note n="y" place="margin">Dan. 5.5.</note> 
                     <hi>hand writing</hi> in the wall marred <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzars</hi> feaſt, ſo will death marre the wicked mans mirth.</p>
                  <p>It will rob him of all his pompe, as<note n="z" place="margin">Dan. 4.30.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> was turned from his glorious Palace, to eate graſſe like an Oxe; ſo will death turne the profane man out of all his dignities, bring his<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 14.11.</note> pompe to the grave, and make him a<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 25.41.</note> companion with the Devill and his angels.</p>
                  <p>It will leave him as an abomination upon the earth, his memory ſhall<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 10.7.</note> rot, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as a dead beaſt caſteth an ill ſavour
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18473:17"/> when he dyeth, ſo the man that is in<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 49.23.</note> honour, and knoweth not, is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of God, deſtitute of his feare, void of his grace, ſhall be like the beaſt which periſheth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> It ſhall be the beginning of thoſe miſeries which never ſhall have end, it ſhall intangle them in that ſnare whence there is no eſcaping, and bring them to thoſe burnings, where is no<note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 16.24.</note> quenching; to that<note n="f" place="margin">Jude v. 7.</note> fire which is everlaſting, it ſhall caſt them into that<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 21.8.</note> lake, from whence there is no out-going. To this ſlaughter-houſe muſt thou come, O riotous, O covetous, O uncleane and carnall man, and though thou doeſt eſcape a little while; yet it will not be long: thou mayeſt cheere<note n="h" place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.9.</note> thee in the dayes of thy youth, and walke in the wayes of thy heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes, <hi>but for all theſe things, God at length will bring thee to judgement. Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> ſaith of <hi>Sejanus</hi> horſe, no man ever ſped well that was owner of him: Such a horſe is ſinne, no man ever ſpeeds well at laſt, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18473:17"/> takes a fall that rides this horſe, and is carried head-long to deſtruction; over-whelmed with everlaſting torments, before he is aware of it, over-taken as a woman by her<note n="i" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.3.</note> travaile, it will come as a theefe in the night ſeaſon. As <hi>Abſaloms,</hi> ſervants fell on <hi>Amnon</hi> and murdered him, when his heart was<note n="k" place="margin">2 Sam. 13.28.</note> merry with wine: ſo when the hearts of men are merry with the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſinne, when they be ſatiated and glutted with worldly and fleſhly delights, then ſorrow, ſhame, death, everlaſting woes, the ſervants of ſinne ſhall fall upon them, as <hi>Abſaloms</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants upon <hi>Amnon.</hi> The pleaſures of ſinne are but for a<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> ſeaſon, they be but a<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 39.5.</note> ſpanne long, as the afflictions of the righteous be but for a<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> moment, ſo the<note n="o" place="margin">Job 20.5.</note> pleaſures and triumph of the wicked: and one houres tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Hell, will ſwallow up the pleaſures of a thouſand yeeres on earth.</p>
                  <p>Are the righteous ſubject to a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> bodily diſſolution? Are they taken away as well as others? Then let
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18473:18"/> the Saints and holy ſervants of God learne, not to ſet their hearts on things here below, but to be as<note n="p" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note> ſtrangers upon the earth; to live as Tenants at will, in a continuall preparedneſſe to depart. The Lord preſſed the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to this, by preſenting before him the changes which hee would worke; <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Lord)<note n="q" place="margin">Jer. 45.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>that which I have built, I will breake downe, and that which J have planted, I will pluck up, even this whole land: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou great things for thy ſelfe? ſeeke them not:</hi> to this the Apoſtle perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the people of God, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their new conditions:<note n="r" place="margin">Col. 3.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>If ye be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek the things which are above:</hi> To this hee urgeth the Hebrewes, by ſetting the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancie of their outward eſtate before them, <hi>Wee have no</hi>
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">Heb 13.12, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Citie here, but ſeeke one to come;</hi> therefore let us goe forth without the Campe, bearing our reproach, let us forſake the Earth, deny our ſelves, be willing to be diſſolved, that wee may enjoy our deſired home.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18473:18"/> And this was of old the exhortation of the Prophet,<note n="t" place="margin">Mica. 2.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Ariſe you and depart, for this is not your reſt:</hi> And therefore as our Saviour ſaid unto the Diſciples concerning <hi>Judas,<note n="v" place="margin">Mat. 26.46.</note> riſe, let us be going, behold he is at hand that doth betray mee:</hi> So let me ſay to you of death, ariſe, let us goe hence, let us take our hearts from things here below, for death which will take our life from us is at hand: And as <hi>Matthew</hi>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">Mat. 9.9.</note> 
                     <hi>aroſe from the receipt of cuſtome, and followed Chriſt:</hi> So let us ariſe every man from his ſinne, from his prophane way, from his evill cuſtome, and become ſincere, humble, diligent, and conſtant fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the Lord Jeſus; and as the <hi>Virgins</hi> at the cry of the Bridegroomes comming, <hi>aroſe</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Prov. 6.10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>and trimmed their lampes:</hi> So we <hi>(Beloved)</hi> hearing now the cry of the comming of death, O let us break off our ſleep, caſt away our ſecurity, prepare our lamps, get the oyle of ſaving grace into our ſoules: Let us not like the ſluggard cry, <hi>yet</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Prov. 6.10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>a little more ſleep, a little more ſlumber, a little more folding of the hands upon the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18473:19"/> bed of ſinne,</hi> leſt, <hi>as poverty came on him as an armed man,</hi> ſo death come on us as an armed man, and take us unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and then we be undone for ever. O therefore ſeeke not peace, ſeeke not fulneſſe, ſeeke not felicity here; as the Angel ſaid of our Saviour,<note n="z" place="margin">Luk 24.5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>he is riſen, he is not here, why ſeeke ye the living among the dead:</hi> ſo may I ſay of theſe things, why ſeeke yee them here below, they are not here, they are above, our God, our Chriſt, our Heaven, our home it is above, and there, O there let our hearts for ever be.</p>
                  <p>Are the righteous ſubject to a bodily diſſolution? Are the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men taken away? Then comfort your ſelves all ye that feare the Lord; there is a Phyſitian comming will heale all your diſeaſes; a Deliverer at hand which will open all priſons; a Conquerour which will overcome all enemies: Therefore let mee charge you in this caſe, as <hi>Moſes</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Iſrael</hi> at the waters of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Exodus</hi> 14.13. <hi>Feare, not, ſtand ſtill,</hi> waite a while, the day
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18473:19"/> of death will come, and when that day commeth, the enemies which you ſee, the miſeries and troubles which you undergoe, you ſhall ſee them, feele them, undergoe them no more for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. It was <hi>Plutarchs</hi> comfort given to his Souldiers, entring into a dangerous and bloudy battell, that they ſhould ſuppe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in a place inviſible; the word ſignifieth, in heaven, in a place of peace and reſt no doubt hemeant. So let us encourage our ſelves, whatſoever be our miſeries, troubles, diſaſters, in the dayes of our life, yet in the Sunne-ſet, in the evening of our age, when death commeth, we ſhall ſup with the Lambe of <hi>God Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> and there will be great joy indeed: for that is the<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 19.7, 8, 9.</note> 
                     <hi>marriage feaſt</hi> of the Lambe and our ſoules, Be therefore patient;<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 10.37.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee that ſhall come; will come, and will not tarrie.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> will remove us when it ſhall be moſt for his glorie and our good: <hi>the righteous ſhall die, the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men ſhall be taken away from the evil to come.</hi> And thus are we come to the third thing.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18473:20"/>
                     <hi>Quare:</hi> why <hi>the righteous die;</hi> why <hi>mercifull men are taken away;</hi> there is evill to come.</q>
                  <p>The <hi>Lord</hi> ſeeth there be many miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, many plagues, and great troubles, as warres, famines, peſtilences, ſtrange and fearfull alterations comming; and to the end holy, righteous, and good men may not ſee theſe evils, feele theſe miſeries, <hi>God</hi> doth take them away. Whence two things preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to our conſideration, 1. <hi>That death is a ſweete mercie, a great kindneſſe to</hi> Gods <hi>holy ſervants.</hi> 2. <hi>That the death, and taking away of holy perſons, is a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prediction of enſuing evils.</hi> Firſt, a word or two of the former of theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>That death is a ſweete mercie, a great kindneſſe to</hi> Gods <hi>holy ſervants.</hi> It is <hi>Salomons Aphoriſme,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Eccle. 7 1</note> 
                     <hi>the day of a mans death, is better then the day of a mans birth:</hi> It is our <hi>Saviours</hi> propoſition,<note n="e" place="margin">Reve. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>bleſſed are they that die in the Lord:</hi> It is Saint <hi>Paules</hi> concluſion,<note n="f" place="margin">Phil 1.23</note> 
                     <hi>to depart and to be with</hi> Chriſt <hi>is farre better.</hi> For</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> By death they are delivered from many incumbent evils, inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18473:20"/> ariſing from the fleſh, from Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, from the world: as the Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at the harveſt removeth the tares from the wheate; as <hi>Abraham</hi> turned ſcoffing and perſecuting<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 21.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſmael</hi> out of the houſe from <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ſo <hi>God</hi> at the day of a good mans death, takes away, turnes out whatſoever might annoy him.</p>
                  <p>By death they are delivered from all enſuſing miſeries: thus before the <hi>Lord</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> brought evill upon the houſe of <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> he tooke away his yong ſonne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>in</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">1 King. 14 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>him was found ſome good thing towards the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Lord</hi> would take him away, he ſhould not ſee the evill enſuing.</p>
                  <p>By death they are brought to the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> of all good,<note n="i" place="margin">Reve. 1.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>all teares are wiped a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> and <hi>in</hi> Gods<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal 16.11.</note> 
                     <hi>preſence there is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of joy, and at his right hand pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> if time would giue leaue to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon it, would therefore teach us, and worke in us, 1. Carefull prepara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion for death. 2. Vehement longings after it. 3. Chearefulneſſe in entertaining
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18473:21"/> it. 4. Moderation in our ſorrow for them that be departed, mourning for our owne loſſe, but rejoycing in their gaine: but to paſſe by this, let us come to the ſecond point.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>The death and taking away of holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, is a fearefull prediction of enſuing evils.</hi> When <hi>Noah</hi> was entred into the Arke, then the<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 7.12 13.</note> Deluge came. When <hi>Lot</hi> was gon out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> then<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 19.24.</note> fire and brimſtone fell upon it and burned it. When the <hi>Lord</hi> had determined the deſtruction of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> houſe, (as you heard before) firſt he tooke away his child, <hi>in whom there was ſome good thing found.</hi> Thus when the <hi>Lord</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to bring evill upon<note n="n" place="margin">2 Kings. 22.16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and upon the people, he would firſt <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good</hi> Ioſiah <hi>the King, (whoſe heart was tender, and humbled himſelfe at the hearing of the Law) to his Fathers, and into his grave with peace,</hi> and then the evill ſhould come. <hi>When</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">2 Chro. 24.18, 24</note> Iehoiada <hi>was dead,</hi> Ioaſh <hi>left the Houſe of the</hi> Lord God <hi>of his Fathers; then the</hi> Syrians <hi>came with a ſmall Companie, and</hi> God <hi>delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a very great Host into their hands,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18473:21"/> &amp; they executed judgement againſt</hi> Ioaſh. The truth of this is moreover manifeſt, by five benefits ariſing to the place where good men are.</p>
                  <p>Their preſence doth draw the love <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> and favour of <hi>God</hi> to the place where they are; they are deare to <hi>God</hi> as the<note n="p" place="margin">Zach. 2.5, 8</note> 
                     <hi>apple of his eye,</hi> and <hi>he will bee a wall of fire about the place where they bee:</hi> and many times doth <hi>God</hi> ſpare the wicked, as the Husbandman ſpareth the<note n="q" place="margin">Mar. 13.30.</note> 
                     <hi>tares,</hi> for the <hi>wheate</hi> growing with them. Thus the Family was ſpared for <hi>Noahs</hi> ſake; and <hi>God</hi> would have ſpared <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> if there had beene<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 18.32</note> 
                     <hi>ten righteous</hi> there: the <hi>Lord</hi> gave<note n="ſ" place="margin">Acts. 27.24</note> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> all them that failed with him, they were delivered from the ſtorme for his ſake. And ſurely, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the<note n="t" place="margin">Verſ. 31.</note> Centurion and the Souldiers, of the Shipmen; <hi>except theſe abide in the ſhippe yee cannot be ſaved:</hi> ſo may I ſay to you of the holy, righteous, and faithfull ſervants of <hi>God,</hi> unleſſe theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide amongſt us we cannot be in ſafetie, we ſhall certainly bee expoſed to many miſeries: for as the Prophet ſaid to <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18473:22"/> were it not for good</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">2 Kin. 3.13</note> Iehoſaphat <hi>I would not looke towards thee;</hi> ſo certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were it not for the preſence of the holy, the mercifull, the righteous, the <hi>Lord</hi> would not looke towards us, at leaſt with any fauourable and ſhining countenance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 
                     <hi>Gods</hi> bleſſing doth attend the place where they are for their ſakes, as the houſe of<note n="w" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.6</note> 
                     <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> was bleſſed for the preſence of the Arke; ſo doth <hi>God</hi> proſper the Kingdome, Towne, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where the righteous are for their ſakes: thus <hi>Laban</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 30.30</note> proſpered through the preſence and ſervice of <hi>Iacob;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> bleſſed<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 29.3, 23</note> 
                     <hi>Potipheas</hi> houſe for <hi>Ioſephs</hi> ſake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> Their performance of religious and holy duties doth cauſe <hi>God</hi> to be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly preſent in the place where they are; if the Father have a child in a Towne, or Family, he will often viſit that place, he will not be ſtrange, but loving and kind to the people dwelling there. So <hi>God,</hi> where his Children are, there will he be graciouſly preſent, thoſe places will he viſit and there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18473:22"/> will ſhew much kindneſſe, and beſtow many favours; for <hi>where two or three be gathered together in his</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 18.20</note> 
                     <hi>Name,</hi> in his feare, according to his word, to invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and worſhip him, <hi>there will he be:</hi> for it is among the<note n="a" place="margin">Rev. 1.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Candleſticks</hi> in the Church, among the beleevers, where the light of the truth ſhineth, where du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of godlineſſe are exerciſed, that <hi>Christ</hi> walked, and ſhewed himſelfe gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly preſent.</p>
                  <p>They are a ſafegard to the place and <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>4</label> people where they are, better then all walles, and Caſtles; then all Armour and Munition; able to doe more by their prayers, then the Souldiers with all their weapons; as <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, <hi>one holy man praying, can doe more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable ſinners can doe with fighting.</hi> Thus <hi>Moſes</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 17 11.</note> prevailed more by his prayers, then <hi>Ioſhua</hi> with all his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers againſt the <hi>Amalekites:</hi> and when the Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> was like to loſe his Army through want of water, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in his Army prevaled with <hi>God,</hi> and obtained raine. As they procure many favours, ſo they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18473:23"/> alſo prevent many evils, which would otherwiſe fall upon the place wher they live:<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 106 23.</note> 
                     <hi>He would</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them, had not</hi> Moſes <hi>his ſervant ſtood before him in the breach to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his wrath, leſt he ſhould deſtroy them.</hi> So that as <hi>Nabals</hi> ſervants ſaid of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and his men,<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam: 25.15, 16</note> 
                     <hi>The men were very good unto us, and we were not hurt, neither miſſed wee any thing as long as wee were converſant with them: when wee were in the field, they were a wall unto us both by night and by day:</hi> ſo may every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Towne, and Family ſay of the holy and righteous ſervants of <hi>God, They have beene very good unto us, and wee have had no hurt while wee have been converſant with them; they have beene a wall unto us, both by night and by day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>5</label> Their example, their counſell, their inſtruction, their wiſedome, their blameleſſe walking, is of great force to reſtraine others from much evill, to allure and draw them (at leaſt) to the outward performance of many good duties: as <hi>Husbands are wonne by the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18473:23"/> converſation of the wives, while they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their chaſte converſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coupled with feare;</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 3.1, 2.</note> wonne to approue of, and attend upon that word of <hi>God,</hi> which teacheth their wives to live ſo chaſtly, to walke ſo circumſpectly, and to order them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves every way ſo holily, ſo meekely, ſo blameleſly, ſo that men that are ſtrangers to the power of a godly life, are ſtrongly wrought upon, and very much affected with, and wonne by the religious and gracious converſation of the <hi>Lords</hi> faithfull people. Even <hi>Saul</hi> will<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.10</note> 
                     <hi>propheſie, when he is among the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi> the coldeſt ſtone will grow hot and full of burning being among the ſtickes in the fire: and <hi>Iustin Martyr</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed he was firſt turned to <hi>Chriſt</hi> by Chriſtian Religion, through the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration he had to behold the innocent and godly life of a Chriſtian, hearing them pray for their good and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who to the utmoſt endevoured and wrought their ruine: thus forcible, thus effectuall, thus prevalent is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a godly converſation. Now by the death of <hi>Gods</hi> people there is a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18473:24"/> removall of theſe priviledges, and ſo the place of their former abode is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to many miſeries: for when the godly are removed, when the righteous are taken away,</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Then Religion and piety faileth, and they become like a people without<note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.</note> the Covenant, without <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the world.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then good Government and even Civility falleth to the ground, like a Houſe without a foundation, then all runneth to ruine like a Shippe without a Pilot: Therefore when the <hi>Lord</hi> would bring confuſion upon <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for her ſinne, what doth hee? He taketh from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 3.1, 2, 3</note> 
                     <hi>Judah</hi> the ſtay and ſtaffe, the whole ſtay of bread, and the whole ſtay of water, the mighty man, and the man of warre, the Iudge, and the Prophet, and the Prudent man, and the Ancient, the Captaine of fifty, and the Honorable man, and the Counſellor, and the cunning Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer, and the eloquent Orator, and <hi>I will give Children to bee their Princes, and Babes ſhall rule over them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18473:24"/>
                  <p>Then there is none to ſtand up in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> gappe, to turne away the wrath of the <hi>Lord</hi> from them, but as Souldiers ruſh in at the breaches made in the walles, when none are ſtanding there to keepe them out; ſo will all manner of plagues and miſeries ruſh in upon the people, when the righteous, who ſhould ſtand in the gap, are taken away from them: therefore when the <hi>Prophets ſaw vanitie, and a lying divination,</hi> when they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke the word of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the people in their ſinne, then the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid, <hi>O Iſrael thy Prophets are like</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Ezek. 13.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>foxes in the De ſarts, yee have not gone up into the gaps, neither made up the hedge, for the houſe of Iſrael to ſtand in the battell, in the day of the</hi> Lord. And againe in another place the <hi>Lord</hi> by the ſame Prophet ſaith,<note n="k" place="margin">Ezek. 22 30, 31</note> 
                     <hi>I ſought for a man among them that ſhould make up the hedge, and ſtand in the gap before me for the Land, that I ſhould not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it, but I found none: therefore have I powred out mine indignation upon them, I have conſumed them all with the fire of my wrath, their owne way have I
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18473:25"/> recompenced upon their heads.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                     </label> This then diſcovereth the folly and impiety of ſuch as love not, deſire not, delight not in the preſence of <hi>Gods</hi> holy and righteous people; whoſe delight is not in then that<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 16.3</note> 
                     <hi>excell in vertue,</hi> as <hi>Chriſts</hi> is; whoſe eyes are not upon the<note n="m" place="margin">Pſa. 101.6.</note> 
                     <hi>faithfull in the Land,</hi> as <hi>Davids</hi> was, but rather wiſh and labour their removall. Many there bee, to whom the preſence of the righteous is like the<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 6 1, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Arke</hi> to the <hi>Philistines;</hi> as that was a burden to their Land, and their <hi>God,</hi> &amp; therefore they ſent it away; ſo are the people of <hi>God</hi> a burden, a trouble to many profane perſons, a croſſe, a contradiction to their doings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire, and labour their abſence: and what doe they hereby, but in the ſtrength of their impiety, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their folly, involve themſelves in remediles and irrecoverable miſeries. The <hi>Sodomites</hi> tooke offence at <hi>Lots</hi> preſence, but what became of them when <hi>Lot</hi> was gone? Did not the<note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 19.24.</note> fire and brimſtone inſtantly conſume them? The preſence of <hi>Moſes</hi> was irkeſome to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18473:25"/> 
                     <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> he was charged no more to looke him in the<note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 10.2, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>face,</hi> but what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued? what was the iſſue of it? were not all the<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 11 5.</note> 
                     <hi>firſt borne</hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon deſtroyed. <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſervants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be a<note n="r" place="margin">Ezod 10 7.</note> ſnare, to be inſtruments of much evill, endevoured their removall; but when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was gone, what became of them? Did not the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Exod. 14</note> 
                     <hi>Red Sea</hi> ſwallow them the very day of <hi>Iſraels</hi> out-going. Thus you ſee how uſually it fares with profane perſons upon the removall of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous: and is it not ſtrange that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this they ſhould ſtill diſtaſte their preſence, ſtill wiſh and worke their abſence? Doe they not hereby plainely declare, and publikely proclaime, 1. That there is no<note n="t" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.1</note> love of <hi>God</hi> in their ſoules, for how can a man love the father, and hate the preſence of the child? 2. That they have no u<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion with <hi>Chriſt;</hi> doe the living mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in a body naturall, hate and wiſh each others removall? <hi>was it ever heard</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that a man did</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Epheſ. 5 29</note> 
                     <hi>hate his owne fleſh;</hi> 3. That there is no ſaving
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18473:26"/> grace, no preſence, no powers of the ſpirit in ſuch; doth not every thing agree with, and rejoyce in its like? Doe not waters agree and flow together in one Chanell? And had theſe men the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of holineſſe in them, could they grieve at the preſence of <hi>Gods</hi> people? Surely it is impoſſible; for the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> is a Spirit of<note n="w" place="margin">Phil. 2.1, 2</note> fellowſhip, love, peace, joy, making men of one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and of one minde; and when the righteous are gone, when the <hi>mercifull men are taken away,</hi> who ſhall ſtand in the gap then? Shall the profane, ſhall the worker of iniquity? What can he doe; In what account are his prayers? The blind man could ſee and ſay this; <hi>God heareth not</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Ioh. 9 31.</note> 
                     <hi>ſinners;</hi> their <hi>prayers are an</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Prov. 28.9</note> 
                     <hi>abomination in his preſence,</hi> as <hi>Salomon</hi> doth aſſure us.</p>
                  <p>This muſt therefore teach us deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to bewaile, and much to lament the loſſe of godly men, when they are taken from us; and to feare the evils like to enſue upon their departure; <hi>O Beloved,</hi> let us not, I beſeech you, be like them of whom the Propht here ſpeaketh, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18473:26"/> did not conſider, that did not <hi>lay to heart the taking away of the righteous from enſuing evils.</hi> Let us not be like <hi>Ephraim, whoſe ſtrength was devoured by</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Hoſ. 7.9</note> 
                     <hi>ſtrangers, and he knew it not,</hi> that <hi>had gray haires here and there, and much weakeneſſe comming upon him, and yet he knew it not:</hi> O let us not be unſenſible of the declining and decay of our ſtrength and ſtay, and of the miſeries which are comming on us; let us not be like a man in a <hi>Lethargy,</hi> that hath no feeling of the cutting off, and taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of a member from him: but rather as <hi>David</hi> upon the fall of <hi>Abner</hi> refuſed to eate till the Sunne was gone downe, ſaying to his ſervants,<note n="a" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.35, 38, 39.</note> 
                     <hi>know ye not that there is a Prince, and a great man fallen this day in Iſrael, and I am this day weake, and theſe men the ſonnes of</hi> Zervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah <hi>be too hard for me:</hi> may not wee ſay the like in this behalfe; is not the Church of <hi>God</hi> weake, are not the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thereof too ſtrong? Was not the man now fallen amongſt us a Ruler, an eminent man in this place? And is there not in this regard great cauſe of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18473:27"/> mourning? Doubtleſſe there is. For whenſoever a good man doth fall; 1. The Church of <hi>God</hi> on earth doth loſe one member. 2. The place where they lived doth loſe one Pillar, and ſo, like a houſe whoſe pillars faile, is much weakned. 3. Hereby we looſe his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, which was a whetſtone to ſet<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 27.17.</note> edge upon us, whoſe face was, as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſaid of <hi>Eſaus, as the</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 33.10.</note> 
                     <hi>face of God</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us. 4. Hereby we loſe his prayers, which were as buckets to bring much water out of the wells of Salvation to us. 5. Wee loſe his inſtructions and counſels, which were as a ſhining Lampe, as a comfortable Guide to us in the way. 6 Wee loſe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, which were wont to be as the <hi>Apothecaries</hi> oyntments, as the ſweete flowers of the Garden to our noſtrils, as the <hi>Dove</hi> with her <hi>Olive</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 8.11</note> 
                     <hi>branch</hi> to <hi>Noah;</hi> as the Wagons which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſent to old <hi>Iacob,</hi> the reviving of ours, as they were the<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 45.27, 28.</note> reviving of his heart. 7. We loſe his helpe and aſſiſtance, which was wont like a ſtrong arme to make our heavy burthen light, as a fountaine of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18473:27"/> living water to refreſh us, as a firme &amp; ſure anker to ſtay us: &amp; therfore as <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Deu. 34.8.</note> wept 30. dayes for <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo have you great cauſe of ſorrow and lamentation now for the taking away of this <hi>Moſes,</hi> this ſervant of the <hi>Lord</hi> here before us: and alſo at other times whenſoever the righteous doe thus periſh, <hi>are thus taken away from the evils enſuing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now to ſay no more, here you ſee a ſhining ſtarre in your Horizon ſet, a maine Pillar of your houſe fallen, a choice flower of your Garden taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, a man eminent for his endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, well known, &amp; ſufficiently tryed for his abilities: a man of whom; 1. For his Religion, for his uprightneſſe towards <hi>God</hi> I thinke I may ſay of him, as the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf of <hi>Iob,</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Iob 1.1.</note> 
                     <hi>He was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and upright man, one that feared</hi> God, <hi>and eſchewed evill,</hi> a man that held faſt his<note n="h" place="margin">Iob. 2.3.</note> integrity, though there wanted not occaſions and meanes to move and ſhake him; as <hi>Satan</hi> moved <hi>God</hi> againſt <hi>Iob</hi> without cauſe to deſtroy him; a man he was like the tree growing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Courts of the <hi>Lords</hi> houſe,<note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 92.12.</note> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18473:28"/> much fruit in his old age. 2. For his publike Government, hee was like them preſcribed by <hi>Iethro</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Exo. 12.21</note> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> an able man, a man fearing <hi>God,</hi> a man of truth, &amp; hating covetouſneſſe: a man in whom there was a ſweet and powerfull concurrence of all requiſite vertues for his calling and office and accordingly he proved a carefull Watch-man over this Towne and people: he did not like the evill ſervant hide his<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 25.30</note> talent in a nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin; but his care, ſtudy, labour, travell was (I am perſwaded) for the publike, common, and true good of this place and people. 3. He was in his domeſticke Government like<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 18.19</note> 
                     <hi>Abraham,</hi> a man commanding, and teaching his children and houſehold after him to walke in the wayes of the <hi>Lord;</hi> a man like <hi>David</hi> walking in the middeſt of his<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 101.3.</note> houſe with a perfect heart. 4. Hee was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Gods</hi> people kinde, loving, &amp; amiable, ſhewing that his<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 16.3.</note> 
                     <hi>delight was in them that excell in vertue.</hi> 5. Hee was in his conference &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication, wiſe, grave, holy, full of heavenly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.7</note> 
                     <hi>his lippes did diſperſe knowledge.</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:18473:28"/> I ſpeake theſe things not to diſparage any living, but to encourage ſuch as knew him, to a carefull imitation of what was found praiſe-worthy in him. The richer his endowments, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your loſſe; the more ſhould bee your griefe, the greater your care to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the reparation, and to ſtop the breach which <hi>God</hi> hath made by his fall: and whatſoever you have loſt in him, labour to repaire and increaſe in your ſelves. 1. By growing in all grace, by being filled with all goodneſſe, drawing nearer to <hi>God,</hi> in all things make his counſell your<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 73.24.</note> guide now, that he may receive you to his glory at the laſt. 2. By being diligent, faithfull, careful, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable in the imployment you have received, that ſo when you ſhall be as he is now, you may heare that ſweete and comfortable ſaying of our Saviour,<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 25.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Well done thou good and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, thou haſt beene Ruler over few things, I will make thee Ruler over many things; enter thou into the joy of thy</hi> LORD.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18473:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18473:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>ELIAHS FIERY CHARIOT OR THE HOLY MANS TRIVMPH after Death.</p>
                  <p>A SERMON PREACHED at Plimouth the nineteenth of Auguſt 1631. At the Funerall of the late faithfull and worthy Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt, MATTHIAS NICOLS Bachelour in Divinity, and late Preacher to the Towne of <hi>Plimouth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>A. G.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 Sam. 25.1.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And <hi>SAMVEL</hi> dyed, and all the Iſraelites were gathered together, and lamented him, and buried him in his houſe at <hi>Ramah.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Printed at <hi>LONDON,</hi> 1640.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18473:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:18473:30"/>
                  <head>ELIAHS FIERY CHARET OR, The holy mans Tryumph after DEATH.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>2 Kings 2.11.12.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Behold there appeared a Charet of fire, and horſes of fire, and parted them both aſunder, and <hi>Eliah</hi> went up by a whirle-wind into Heaven.</p>
                        <p>And <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaw it, and he cryed, my Father, my Father, the Charet of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the horſemen thereof.</p>
                        <p>And hee ſaw him no more: and hee tooke hold of his own cloathes, and rent them in two pieces.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſorrowes of <hi>Gods</hi> people are often like the waves of the Sea, one rowling upon the backe of another; like ſtones in a building, when one is fallen, another tumbles after: Wee multiply
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18473:31"/> our tranſgreſſions, and God doth mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply our miſeries; we are ſometimes like men caſt into a deepe and dead ſlumber, and God muſt ſtrike not once but twice before we will awaken: our hearts are often very ſenſeleſſe, ſtony, ſtupid; and therefore as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtroke the rock<note n="a" place="margin">Num. 20.11.</note> 
                     <hi>twice, that waters might come forth,</hi> ſo doth God often ſtrike us, ſometimes in the feete, in our Inferiours; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the ſides, in them that are moſt deare unto us; ſometimes in the armes, in them that be our chiefe Aſſiſtants; ſometimes in the head, in them that are our Governours ſometimes in the face, in the eye the tendereſt part, in our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor: and all this the Lord doth to draw from us the teares of true repentance.</p>
                  <p>I have beene to you of this place of late a Meſſenger, like<note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 18</note> 
                     <hi>Cuſhi</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> bringing nothing but ſad and ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tydings of the fall of your friends and acquaintance; like the Meſſengers comming to <hi>Iob</hi> one after another, with<note n="c" place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> tydings of taking away the ſheepe, oxen aſſes, the death and ſlaughter of his ſervants, ſonnes, and daughters. It was but on Tueſday laſt I brought you
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18473:31"/> heavy tydings of the death of a pious and eminent Magiſtrate, and now am come again with the like ſad and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meſſage, of the death and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of your holy, faithfull, and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, Paſtor: Of whom whiles they lived, I may ſay as <hi>David</hi> did of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.22.</note> 
                     <hi>from the blood of the ſlain, and the fat of the mighty, the bow of</hi> Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than <hi>turned not backe, and the ſword of</hi> Saul <hi>returned not empty:</hi> ſo theſe, The ſword of the one in the <hi>Magiſtracie,</hi> and the Bow of the other in the <hi>Miniſtery</hi> proſpered and prevailed mightily: of that ſweet communion which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them, of the unparallel'd inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of their converſations, agility, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, un-weariedns in their callings, I may ſpeak againe in the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> touching <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1.23.</note> 
                     <hi>They were lovely &amp; pleaſant in their lives, and in their death they were not divided; they were ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eagles, they were ſtronger the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lyons.</hi> And as to you who lately enjoyed the benefit, the comfort of their preſence, labours, abilities, I may ſay once againe with <hi>David</hi> there, Ver. 24. <hi>Yee daughters of</hi> Iſrael <hi>weepe over</hi> Saul, <hi>who clothed you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18473:32"/> in ſcarlet with other delights, who put on ornaments of gold upon your apparell; how are the mighty fallen in the midſt of battel?</hi> So in this caſe; O Town, O People, O Congregation, weepe over theſe men, who lately ſought your welfare, ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed your good, were inſtruments of your peace, of your honour, of your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richment: whoſe endevours, whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, whoſe labours were to adorne you with the choiſeſt ornaments, and to fill you with the ſweeteſt delights. O how are theſe mighty men fallen in the middeſt of this Battell! And touching him whoſe corps lyeth now before us, we may all ſay as <hi>David</hi> of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> Verſe 26. <hi>Wee are diſtreſſed for thee,</hi> O holy, and godly Paſtor, O zealous and and painfull Miniſter, <hi>very pleaſant haſt thou beene to us, thy love to us was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, paſſing the love of Women;</hi> O how is this mighty man fallen! and the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of his war periſhed! And as <hi>Eliſha</hi> in the Text upon the ſight of <hi>Eliahs</hi> tranſlation, ſo may we beholding the diſſolution of this our <hi>Eliah,</hi> cry out, <hi>my Father, my Father, the Charet of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the Horſemen thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18473:32"/>
                  <p>The words declare and ſet before us <hi>Eliahs tranſlation,</hi> aſcenſion into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſignifying (in all probability) the Aſcenſion of our <hi>Saviour:</hi> for as <hi>Eliſha</hi> waited to ſee the tranſlation of <hi>Eliah,</hi> ſo the Diſciples waited, and beheld the<note n="f" place="margin">Acts 1.10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> It ſhadowed alſo our Reſurrection. <hi>Enoch</hi> was tranſlated before the Law, <hi>Eliah</hi> under the Law, Chriſt under the Goſpell; to ſhew that the Believers of alages, before the Law, under the Law, under the Goſpell, ſhall in the appointed time aſcend into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and it likewiſe is a divine, evident and aſſured teſtimony, that all Gods holy people after the paſſage of this earthly pilgrimage, ſhall enjoy life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting in the Kingdome of Heaven.</p>
                  <p>In the words ſome things require a little explication; By the <hi>Charets of fire, and Horſes of fire,</hi> is meant the Angels of God likened to <hi>Charets</hi> and <hi>Horſes.</hi> 1. For their ſtrength. 2. For their valour. 3. For their fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Church of God, and againſt the enemies thereof. 4. For their readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſpeed, and quickneſſe in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of Gods counſels. 5. For their
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18473:33"/> order, ſubmiſſion, and ſubjection unto God, they are not like horſes in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen field running whither they liſt; but like horſes in a Charet, going when whither, and which way the Lord will have them. They are ſaid to bee <hi>Horſes of fire, &amp; Charets of fire,</hi> to ſhew that they are zealous, fervent, earneſt, and full of life and power, as the burning fire, in the execution of their office. Thus by the Prophet <hi>Zacharie</hi> they are likened to<note n="g" place="margin">Zach. 6.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>horſes and Charets comming out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the mountaines,</hi> to ſhew that they come forth with reſolution, courage, preparednes in a ſpeedy manner to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute Gods Will and Counſell, which is firme like the Mountaines: and by the Apoſtle they are ſtiled a<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>flaming fire,</hi> and by the Prophet <hi>Iſajah</hi> they are called<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 6.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Seraphin, ab urendo;</hi> to ſhew their fervor in the way and worke wherein the Lord doth ſet them: and for this alſo they are reſembled to the wind, becauſe as the wind is a ſtrong and ſpeedy meſſenger, ſo are the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of the Lord: and herein we may clearely ſee, that the more ſtrong, cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, ſpeedy, obedient and fervent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18473:33"/> we are in our callings, the more doe we reſemble the holy Angels.</p>
                  <p>The words thus explained, fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder into two generall parts.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item n="1">
                        <label>1. <hi>Eliahs</hi> Tranſlation.</label>
                        <q>Behold there appeared a Charet of fire, and horſes, of fire, and parted them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder, and Eliah went up by a whirle wind into Heaven.</q>
                     </item>
                     <item n="2">
                        <label>2. <hi>Eliſha's</hi> Lamentation.</label>
                        <q>And Eliſha ſaw it, and he cryed: my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, my Father, the Charets of Iſrael, and the Horſemen thereof: And he ſaw him no more: and hee tooke hold of his own cloths, and rent them in two pieces.</q>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>In the firſt of theſe, <hi>Eliahs</hi> Tranſlation, we may conſider;
<list>
                        <item n="1">1. <hi>Motus:</hi> he went up.</item>
                        <item n="2">2. <hi>Terminus a quo,</hi> from whence hee went up, <hi>from the Earth.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item n="3">3. <hi>Terminus ad quem,</hi> to what place he went, <hi>into Heaven.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item n="4">4. <hi>Inſtrumenta motus,</hi> a Charet of fire, Horſes of fire, and a whirle winde.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſecond; <hi>Eliſha's</hi> Lamentation. There is,
<list>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18473:34"/>
                        <item n="1">1. <hi>Motivum:</hi> an Inducement to this lamentation: and this is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: the 1. externall, <hi>hee ſaw it;</hi> the 2. internall, his affection: <hi>my Father, my Father:</hi> the 3. mixt, or experimentall, drawne from the defence miniſtred to <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Eliah,</hi> whereof <hi>Eliſha</hi> was very ſenſible, and therefore called him, the <hi>Horſemen and Charet of</hi> Iſrael.</item>
                        <item n="2">2. Here is <hi>Gradus,</hi> the degree of his griefe, nor a little, but much, <hi>hee cryed.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item n="3">3. <hi>Incrementum doloris,</hi> the increaſe of his ſorrow, that <hi>hee ſhould ſee him no more.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item n="4">4. <hi>Signum,</hi> the ſigne of his griefe and ſorrow, <hi>hee tooke hold of his owne Cloths, and rent them in two pieces.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee the words are like a Tree of many branches, each bearing his particular fruit, of ſome of which we will take a more ſlender, of others a fuller taſte: and firſt to begin with the firſt thing noted in <hi>Eliahs</hi> Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18473:34"/>
                  <p>The <hi>terminus à quo,</hi> from whence he aſcended, <hi>from the earth:</hi> when <hi>Eliah,</hi> and <hi>Eliſha</hi> were walking together, the Charet of fire, and Horſes of fire parted them aſunder, and <hi>Eliah</hi> went up to heaven, he was carried up from the earth: thereby ſhewing,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the earth is not the abiding place of Gods people;</hi> 
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 13.14.</note> 
                     <hi>We have no continuing City here</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>but ſeeke one to come:</hi> 1. This is an enemies countrey, Satan is ſtiled <hi>the</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4.</note> 
                     <hi>God of this world:</hi> here we are<note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 15.19.</note> 
                     <hi>hated,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Jacob,</hi> when he beheld that <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban's</hi> countenance was not towards him<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 31.2</note> as before, that he had ten times chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his wages, tooke his wives, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>, and returned to his owne Countrey; ſo we beholding how the world doth frowne upon us, how it doth exerciſe us with many changes, we ſhould willingly forſake it, and gladly go to our heavenly home. 2. Our Chriſt, our Jeſus is<note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 24.6</note> 
                     <hi>riſen, aſcended, he is not here,</hi> and therefore as the Bee reſteth not till he returne to his Hive, as the<note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 8.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Dove</hi> found no reſting place till ſhe came againe unto the Arke, no
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18473:35"/> more ſhould we till we returne to our God, and our Jeſus, and have the full fruition of their bleſſed preſence in the heavens. 3. Our portion is not in this life, the men of the world have their<note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 17.14.</note> portion here, our<note n="r" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Inheritance is reſerved for us in the heavens:</hi> O there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us not <hi>labour for the bread which doth</hi>
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioh. 6.27.</note> 
                     <hi>periſh; let us not lay up for our ſelves treaſure upon</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 6.19 20.</note> 
                     <hi>earth, where the ruſt and the moath corrupt, and where theeves break thorough and ſteale, but let us lay up for our ſelves treaſure in heaven.</hi> For this is the <hi>terminus ad quem;</hi> the place where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto we muſt move, as <hi>Eliah</hi> here did.</p>
                  <p>It is not long ſince <hi>Eliah</hi> ranne<note n="u" place="margin">1 Kin. 18.45, 46.</note> on foote, and <hi>Ahab</hi> rode in his Charet; but now <hi>Eliah</hi> he hath a Charet, a Charet of fire, and Horſes of fire, a bright, a glorious, and ſhining Charet, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of bleſſed Angels to carry him into the holy and higheſt heavens. Let <hi>Ahab</hi> ride now, <hi>Eliah</hi> ſhall ride at the laſt. Gods people ſhall have their Charets one day as well as others. And here note:</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>That the future eſtate of Gods ſervants
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18473:35"/> ſhall be very glorious, though for the preſent it be contemptible, and ignominious in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall appearance:</hi> the greateſt honour of Gods ſervants is reſerved till after their departure out of this earthly pilgrimage. Now indeed like <hi>Eliah,</hi> they walke on foote, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> laſt they ſhall be like <hi>Eliah</hi> in his fiery Charet; how they be like <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in priſon, then they ſhall be like <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ruling in the ſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> place in the Kingdome; for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they ſhall be next to God and Chriſt in the Kingdome of Heaven. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Salomon</hi> had ſeene of old,<note n="*" place="margin">Eccl. 10 7</note> 
                     <hi>ſervants upon horſes, and Princes walking as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants upon the earth:</hi> ſo now, men that are ſlaves to their owne luſts, bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to Satan; ſervants, yea drudges to the world, theſe are on horſe-backe, exalted, preferred, endowed with earthly riches, worldly honours, but they who are <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> theſe walke like <hi>ſervants</hi> on foote, theſe are in a low and deſpiſed eſtate for the moſt part; but there is a day comming wherein the Lord will diſpell all the clouds of ignominy now covering them, and cauſe a glorious Sunne to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18473:36"/> ſhine upon them: they ſhall then have a very glorious dwelling,<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.1</note> a dwelling in the heavens, a dwelling made without hands, a City whoſe<note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 11.10.</note> 
                     <hi>builder</hi> and <hi>maker</hi> is <hi>God,</hi> a dwelling ſo rich, ſo beautifull, ſo ſumptuous, that in compariſon here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the<note n="z" place="margin">Dan. 4.30</note> Palace whereof <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> ſo boaſted, is but a baſe Cottage. Then they ſhall have a<note n="a" place="margin">Luke 25.43.</note> 
                     <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> in reſpect whereof the moſt delightfull places, the pleaſanteſt garden upon earth, are but a barren wilderneſſe: then they ſhall have treaſure, in reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> whereof the choiſeſt jewels are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> dung and droſſe, ſuch a tree to gather fruit from, as in regard thereof, the chiefe Vines are but brambles, and thornes, and briars, ſuch a well-ſpring to drinke of, as in compariſon thereof, the ſweeteſt Wine is but ſlimy water, as it is very fully expreſſed by our<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 22.1, 2.</note> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.1, 2. for then as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nihil deerit, nihil oberit, omne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderium eorum Chriſtus praeſens implebit, non ſeneſcent, non tabeſcent, non putreſcent ampliùs, perpetua ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>, foelix aeteruitat beatitudinis illis ſufficientiam confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e</hi> then nothing ſhall be wanting,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18473:36"/> there ſhall be nothing which ſhall hurt: the bleſſed face and preſence of Jeſus Chriſt ſhall fully ſatisfie all their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, &amp;c. For</p>
                  <p>Then there ſhall be deliverance from all ſin, then there ſhal be gardens with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> weeds, trees without either ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous branch, or withered leafe, then there ſhall be garments<note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 5.26</note> without either ſpot or wrinkle, as<note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 14 25.</note> 
                     <hi>Abſolon</hi> was ſaid to be without bodily blemiſh, from the crowne of the head to the ſole of his feete; ſo ſhall Gods people at laſt be without all blemiſh both in their ſoules, and alſo in their bodies; now they are as the Moone bright and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, yet as the Moone, ſo they have their ſpots, and are ſubject to ſpirituall waxings, and wanings, but at laſt they ſhall be as the Sun, wholly, unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably pure, glorious, in an eſtate more excellent then the eſtate of <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency: in him there was a <hi>poſſe cadere,</hi> a poſſibility to fall, but <hi>Gods</hi> people ſhall be confirmed as the Angels of <hi>God,</hi> ſo that they ſhall be free from a poſſibility to be drawne to ſinne.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18473:37"/>
                  <p>Then there ſhall be a diſcharge from all weakneſſes, maladies, diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, diſorders of nature, evils and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences whatſoever; then there ſhall be a ceſſation from all<note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 21.4.</note> 
                     <hi>labour,</hi> a removall of all ſorrowes, the<note n="f" place="margin">Rev. 21.4.</note> 
                     <hi>firſt things ſhall paſſe away,</hi> the miſeries, troubles, and changes attending this life ſhall be gone, like a Land floud that paſſeth by, like a cloud driven away by the wind, they ſhall be waſted away in death, done away in the grave, as the<note n="g" place="margin">2 King. 5.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Leproſie</hi> of <hi>Naaman</hi> in <hi>Iordan:</hi> they ſhall have an abſolute and bleſſed free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from all evils both inward and outward, of the body and of the ſoule, for they<note n="h" place="margin">Rev. 7.16 17.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall hunger no more, neither ſhall thirſt any more, neither ſhall the Sunne light on them nor any heat, for the Lambe which is in the midſt of the throne ſhall feed them, and ſhall leade them unto living fountaines of water, and God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>3</label> Then they ſhall have victory over all enemies, then all adverſarie powers ſhall vaniſh like ſmoake before the Sunne, and flie like the<note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 17</note> 
                     <hi>Philiſtin</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iſrael:</hi> now as <hi>Iſrael</hi> had the<note n="k" place="margin">Iude 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites,</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:18473:37"/> ſo have we them that be thornes in our ſides, and prickes in our eyes, now we are<note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 12 7.</note> 
                     <hi>buffeted</hi> by Satan, now we are troubled with the <hi>pricke in the fleſh:</hi> but then<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 16 20.</note> 
                     <hi>Satan ſhall be tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under our feete,</hi> then our enemies ſhall be made our<note n="n" place="margin">Math. 22 44.</note> 
                     <hi>foot-ſtoole,</hi> then we ſhall have a perpetuall tryumph, we ſhall not feare an enemy, nor looſe a friend.</p>
                  <p>Then they ſhall have the fruition of <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>4</label> all good, a glorious dwelling, a City of pure gold, the foundation of the walles garniſhed with precious ſtones; and the gates thereof of pearles, as our <hi>Saviour</hi> at large deſcribeth it,<note n="o" place="margin">Revel. 21 17, 18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Revel.</hi> 21. to ſhew that nothing is ſo precious, ſo bright, ſo glorious, ſo rich, ſo deare to us, as can ſufficiently ſet out the tranſcendent and unconceiveable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of that heavenly City: then alſo ſhall we have the ſweete commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Saints; were the dwelling never ſo glorious, ſhould a man be conſtrained to dwell alone, it would prove a great abatement of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, delight, and comfort: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the filling up of the joy of his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18473:38"/> ſervants, <hi>God</hi> hath provided for them not onely glorious manſions, but alſo the comfortable communion of his Saints and Angels: <hi>they ſhall</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Mat 8.11 Heb. 12.22 23.</note> 
                     <hi>ſit downe with Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob,</hi> they ſhall come to an innumerable company of Angels, to the generall Aſſembly, and Church of the firſt borne, &amp;c. And which is moſt of all, more then all the reſt, they ſhall have the bleſſed viſion of <hi>God:</hi> a glorious houſe, the company of the children, there is little; without the preſence of the Maſter of the houſe, the Father of the Family: ſo heaven, ſo the communion of the Saints, were little; ſhould we not alſo behold the face of <hi>God;</hi> for as the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the husbands preſence, the ſence of the husbands love doth more ſolace, ſatisfie, rejoyce, and delight the wife, then the ſtatelineſſe of the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, the preſence of all her compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: ſo the fruition of <hi>Gods</hi> face and favour, the <hi>Lord</hi> filling the ſoule with his celeſtiall brightneſſe and glory, we ſeeing him face to face, and he becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all in all unto us, this is much more then all the reſt; and herein ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18473:38"/> the perfection, the conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our happineſſe, therefore our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith,<note n="q" place="margin">Rev. 22, 3, 4.</note> 
                     <hi>there ſhall bee no more curſe, but the Throne of God, and of the Lambe ſhall bee in it, and his ſervants ſhall ſerve him, and they ſhall ſee his face.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if the future eſtate of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants be ſo honourable, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                     </label> ſo full of all ſatisfaction, ſo glorious; why are they ſo willing to continue upon the face of the Earth? Will any man deſire to continue in a wilderneſſe, when hee may live in a glorious Paradiſe? to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in an enemies Country, when he may enjoy all fulneſſe in his fathers houſe? to live in a priſon, when he may partake of the ſweeteſt free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</p>
                  <p>The people of God deſire long life; <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
                     </label> 1. Sometimes for the making of their<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 39.13.</note> 
                     <hi>peace</hi> with God more fully before they finiſh this earthly pilgrimage. 2. Sometimes they may alſo glorifie God with their bodies, which by death are<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 6.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>diſabled</hi> to doe God any ſervice. 3. Sometimes that they may among men<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 30.10. Pſal. 84.10 11, 12.</note> 
                     <hi>celebrate</hi> and praiſe God for his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings and favours beſtowed upon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18473:39"/> them, that they may be an encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Gods people, anornament to Gods truth, a terror to the adverſaries of it here upon earth. 4. Sometimes that they may perfect <hi>ſome good Worke</hi> which they have begun, do good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their places and callings: thus<note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul,</hi> though he knew <hi>it was better for him to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt,</hi> yet he was willing to live longer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>it was good for them that hee ſhould continue with them:</hi> ſo that though the people of God ſometimes for ſuch cauſes doe deſire continuance here, yet it no way denieth this truth, that their future eſtate in the Heavens is very glorious. And if ſo be, their future eſtate be ſo glorious, ſo pleaſant, ſo comfortable, as we have clearely ſeene it is, Then firſt,</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> This muſt teach the people of God patience under their preſent burthens, troubles, tryals, miſeries; the joy is behind the glory, the <hi>Crowne is</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>layd up for hereafter;</hi> here like <hi>Iſrael</hi> we have but a little taſte, a few<note n="x" place="margin">Num. 13.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Grapes</hi> in the way, the full <hi>Vintage</hi> is reſerved till at laſt; here we are like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18473:39"/> Honey we have is in the<note n="y" place="margin">Judg. 14.14.</note> 
                     <hi>belly</hi> of a <hi>Lyon,</hi> but hereafter we ſhall have ſweet without ſowre, light without darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, rivers of joy without a tempeſt: therefore as the ſervant patiently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth the heate of the day, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of his wages in the evening; the Souldier the dangerous and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wounds of the battell, in expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Crowne; the husband-man the heate of the Summer, the cold of the Winter, comforting himſelfe with the comming of a full and liberall harveſt: let us doe the like in this caſe, here is a wages, a crowne, a harveſt, which will abundantly anſwer all loſſes, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, hardneſſe, reproaches, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth for the preſent annoy us. As our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaid in another caſe, <hi>a</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">John 16.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Woman when ſhee is in travell hath ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, becauſe her houre is come, but as ſoone as ſhe is delivered of the child, ſhee remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth no more the anguiſh, for joy that a man is borne into the World:</hi> ſo in this caſe the people of God are now often in great anguiſh, like a woman in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell but when this life is ended, when our regeneration and new birth ſhall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18473:40"/> be fully accompliſhed, we ſhall meete with that which will ſwallow up all our former griefe and trouble, and make it as if it had never beene: and as <hi>Salomons</hi> mother ſaid in that caſe,<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 31.6 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. <hi>give ſtrong drinke to him that is ready to periſh, and wine to thoſe that bee of a heavy heart; let him drinke and forget his poverty, &amp; remember his miſery no more:</hi> ſo here is a cup of conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, here is ſweet wine, here is a more pure river, whereof when wee once come to drinke our full draught, we ſhall forget our poverty, we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our miſery no more: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us according to the charge of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 37.5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>commit our way to God, truſt in him, and the Lord ſhall bring it to paſſe, hee ſhall bring forth our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as the light, and our judgement as the noone day:</hi> and in all our troubles, tryals, and againſt all adverſary powers, let us ſay as the Prophet <hi>Micah</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Mica. 7.8 9.</note> doth, <hi>rejoyce not againſt mee, O mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, when I fall, I ſhall riſe; when I ſit in darkeneſſe, the Lord ſhall bee a light unto mee: I will beare the indignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18473:40"/> untill he plead my cauſe, and execute judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for me: he will bring me forth to the light, and I ſhall behold his righteouſneſſe.</hi> And reckon alſo with the<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> 
                     <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that the <hi>ſufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared to the glory which ſhall be revealed in us:</hi> &amp; evermore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>our light afflictions which are but for a moment, worketh for us a far more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding &amp; eternall waight of glory: while we look not at the things which are, but at the things w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are not ſeene, for the things which are ſeen are temporall, but the things w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are not ſeene are eternall:</hi> thinke I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you of theſe things and let pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence have her<note n="f" place="margin">Jam. 1.4.</note> 
                     <hi>perfect work</hi> in all tryals, troubles, changes, where with the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall be pleaſed to exerciſe you.</p>
                  <p>This muſt teach the children of <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> God conſtancy in the way and worke of God: there is a bleſſed Price at the end of this race, there is joy, peace, glory, fulnes, unutterable,<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa 64.4.</note> inconceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: O therefore bee not like <hi>Gideons</hi> many thouſands which<note n="h" place="margin">Judg. 7.5, 6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>fainted,</hi> which <hi>bowed downe upon their knees, and drunke of the waters,</hi> and ſo were diſcarded
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18473:41"/> as unfit for the battell: be not afraid of any loſſe, of any trouble, of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, having given your names to God; O bow not downe againe to the World, be no more as ſervants to your luſts, or drudges to the earth: I beſeech you ſay not with the ſluggard,<note n="i" place="margin">Prov. 26.13.</note> 
                     <hi>there is a Lyon in the way, a Lyon in the ſtreete,</hi> feare not the Lyon of oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of reproach, of earthly loſſe, or tranſitory trouble, but goe on in the way of God, be faithfull in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord, be couragious in the ſervice of our God: and then as the ſpirit of the Lord came<note n="k" place="margin">Judg. 14.5, 6, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>mightily</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Sampſon,</hi> ſo mightily, <hi>that he rent the Lyon in pieces which roared againſt him,</hi> and found at length a <hi>Honey combe in the belly of him:</hi> ſo ſhall the Lord inable you to vanquiſh all oppoſitions, and draw very ſweete comforts from your preſent diſquietments. Let not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe take hold of you,<note n="l" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> 
                     <hi>the Dog is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned againe to his vomit, and the Sow to her wallowing in the mire;</hi> be not like<note n="m" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.19.20.</note> 
                     <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus;</hi> like unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and cowardly marriners, that flie back or make ſhipwracke with every
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18473:41"/> tempeſt: doe not with<note n="n" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Demas</hi> forſake <hi>Paul,</hi> leave the Miniſtery, become a ſtranger to the word, and forſake God, and goe back againe to this preſent World: be not like the diſciples, which followed Chriſt for the<note n="o" place="margin">John 6.66.</note> 
                     <hi>loaves,</hi> but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards went backe, and came no more to him: but like <hi>Gideons</hi> 300. Souldiers, goe yee on without fainting, without bowing down to the World: reſolve in this, as <hi>Heſter</hi> did in that caſe,<note n="p" place="margin">Heſter 4.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Heſter</hi> 4. <hi>If I periſh, I periſh,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you looſe, whatſoever you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, here is an ample recompence: be you faithfull, be you upright, be yee conſtant as <hi>Eliah</hi> was, and you ſhall at laſt have a <hi>fiery Charet</hi> as <hi>Eliah</hi> had. Walke with God without wavering, as<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Noah</hi> did, as he ceaſed not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> building the <hi>Arke,</hi> whatſoever diſcouragement was miniſtred, no more doe you ceaſe to ad grace to grace, as the builders doe ſtone to ſtone, till you attaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection: and then as <hi>Noah</hi> had his <hi>Arke,</hi> was preſerved in it when others pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, ſo ſhall you have ſafety, peace, joy, comfort, and everlaſting tryumph, when others ſhall periſh in the deluge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18473:42"/> of Gods judgements. Be conſtant as<note n="r" place="margin">1 Sam. 17 33.34.</note> 
                     <hi>David</hi> was, and then as he overcame the <hi>Beare,</hi> the <hi>Lyon,</hi> the great <hi>Goliah,</hi> and enjoyed the Crowne at length, ſo ſhall we the Crowne of glory at the laſt, if we<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rev. 2.10</note> 
                     <hi>be faithfull unto the death:</hi> therefore with <hi>Moſes</hi> ſeeing him that is<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 11.26, 27.</note> 
                     <hi>inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> and <hi>having an eye to the recompence,</hi> let us <hi>chuſe rather to endure affliction with the children of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon:</hi> and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we have an<note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 10.34.</note> 
                     <hi>abiding ſubſtance in Heaven,</hi> let us with the primitive Chriſtians take the ſpoyling of our goods joyfully. This is the property of true grace, this is peculiar to the man that is truely pious,<note n="w" place="margin">Prov. 4.18.</note> 
                     <hi>to ſhine more and more like the light unto the perfect day:</hi> the Trees of Gods planting be known from all other trees, by <hi>bearing</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Pſ. 92.13.</note> 
                     <hi>much fruit in their old age:</hi> this is that which hath the promiſe, <hi>who ſhall reape but hee that</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Gal. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>fainteth not?</hi> And who ſhall bee ſaved, but he that<note n="z" place="margin">1 Mat. 13.13.</note> 
                     <hi>continueth to the end?</hi> That corne alone which holdeth out unto the harveſt, is gathered into the garner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Is the future eſtate of Gods ſervants
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18473:42"/> ſo pleaſant, ſo eminent, ſo tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently glorious? Then this muſt cauſe the children of God to entertaine death with all cheerefulneſſe; how ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ſo ever in it ſelfe, though it be as the Philoſopher ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of all fearefuls the moſt fearefull; or as <hi>Iob</hi> ſtiles it, the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Job. 18.14</note> 
                     <hi>King of terror:</hi> though looked upon in it ſelfe, it be to the people of God, as once the face of <hi>Eſau,</hi> a terror to <hi>Iacob,</hi> yet look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the glory, dignity, and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of all bliſſe which doth attend it, it ſhould be to the people of God, as the face of <hi>Eſau</hi> was at laſt to <hi>Iacob,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as the<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 33.10, 11.</note> 
                     <hi>face of God:</hi> in the thought of this we ſhould rejoyce, as the hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in his thoughts of the Evening; as the traveller in the thoughts of his bed: as the warriour in the thought of the day of his triumph. For I may ſay to you of <hi>death,</hi> as <hi>Hugh Laverock</hi> ſaid to his fellow Martyr <hi>Iohn a Price</hi> of the <hi>Lord of Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Be of good comfort my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for my Lord of London is our good Phyſitian, he will cure thee of all thy blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and me of my lamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſe this day:</hi> ſo beloved, all yee that truly feare God,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18473:43"/> all that put away all filthineſſe of the fleſh, and perfect holineſſe before him in feare, be of good comfort. <hi>Death</hi> will be your very good Phyſitian, it will cure all your diſeaſes, end all your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, ſet you free from all troubles. And therefore as the people came rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily to<note n="u" place="margin">John 5.4 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Betheſda</hi> to be healed of their infirmities; as we come cheerefully to the Phyſitian; ſo ſhould wee to the grave; for what is death to the people of God? what is it to them to die? but as the Inhabitants leaving of an old and ruinous houſe, the Muſitians laying downe of a Lute whoſe ſtrings are broken, the Carpenters putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of a worne Inſtrument, unfit for any longer ſervice, or imployment; what is <hi>Death</hi> to Gods children, but as a gueſt making haſt out of his Inne to his long, his lovely, and deſired home; as the putting off of a worne, rotten, and ragged ſuite of apparell, to put on rich, and comly rayment; for while we live, we are like<note n="w" place="margin">Zach. 3.3, 4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Joſua the high Prieſt, clothed with filthy garments,</hi> but when we die, then we are like <hi>Ioſua with a fair Mitre upon his head, and comely rayment
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18473:43"/> about his back.</hi> And therefore we ſhould earneſtly deſire to be<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.8.</note> 
                     <hi>abſent from the body, that wee might bee preſent with the Lord.</hi> For the day of <hi>Death</hi> to the body is (as one ſaith) <hi>the birthday</hi> of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to the ſoule: <hi>Seneca</hi> who ſaw the immortality of the ſoule, the future fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity of it, but as through a Cloud, by ifs, and ands, yet profeſſeth, that when hee thought but a little of it, and had ſome pleaſant dreames thereof, hee loathed himſelfe, and all his trifling greatneſſe: <hi>Socrates</hi> alſo ſweetned his cup of poyſon, with his diſcourſe of the <hi>ſoules Immortality,</hi> to the amazement of the beholders: how much more ſhould chriſtian, and ſanctified ſoules be ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, affected, &amp; enflamed with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of it! O how ſhould this cauſe us to thirſt after death, as<note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam. 23, 15, 16.</note> 
                     <hi>David</hi> after the <hi>waters in the wells of Bethlem,</hi> and to breake thorough all difficulties, to attaine that immortall, and ever-bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate which to the people of God attendeth this life, as <hi>Davids</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies brake thorough the hoaſt of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> to fetch them, waters; and as <hi>Laurence Saunders kiſſed the ſtake, and ſaid
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18473:44"/> wilcome be the croſſe of Chriſt, well-come be everlaſting life: my Saviour began to me in a bitter cup, and ſhall I not pledge him?</hi> ſo ſhould wee entertaine death, as a very well-come gueſt, as a very deare friend, our ſoules ſhould ſay within us, <hi>welcome bee death, welcome bee everlaſting life, my Saviour is gone before me, and ſhall I not goe after him?</hi> As the Lyon deſires to goe out of the grate, the Eagle out of the cage, and the priſoner out of the priſon-houſe, ſo ſhould we with <hi>Paul</hi> deſire to be<note n="z" place="margin">Phil. 3.23.</note> 
                     <hi>diſſolved, and to bee with Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> This ſhould moderate our griefe and ſorrow conceived at the departure of our godly friends: For,</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Freedome</hi>
                     </note>1. This is the day of their <hi>Freedome,</hi> who is not comforted to ſee his friend come forth of priſon, to ſee him ſet free from all perſecution and trouble? Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Eliah</hi> went up in his fiery Charet, <hi>Iezabel</hi> could no more make him flie, ſhe had no more power to moleſt and perſecute him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Honour.</hi>
                     </note>2. This is the day of their <hi>Honour,</hi> now with <hi>Eliah</hi> they ride in their fiery Charet into heaven; now as <hi>Salomon</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18473:44"/> ſaid of the<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.12.</note> 
                     <hi>poore wiſe child,</hi> may I ſay of all that are<note n="b" place="margin">2 Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.12.</note> 
                     <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation</hi> though poore, though afflicted, during their abode on earth, yet now they ſhall come out of priſon, out of a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, and low eſtate, to<note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.11, 12.</note> 
                     <hi>reigne with Chriſt in his kingdom.</hi> And I may wel ſay to all that ſorrow for their religious deceaſed friends, as <hi>William Hunter</hi> ſaid to his Mother, when hee was to ſuffer Martyrdome: <hi>For a momentany paine, I ſhall have a crowne of life, and may you not be glad of that?</hi> So they for a ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, troubleſome, contemptible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, have a full, a peaceable, a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious eſtate in heaven, and have in that reſpect great cauſe of rejoycing.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This is the day of their <hi>Ioy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3 <hi>Ioy.</hi>
                     </note> now they are<note n="d" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.19 2 Cor. 11.1, 2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>betrothed,</hi> but then the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage between<note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 19.7.</note> Chriſt and their ſoules ſhall be conſummate; as the <hi>Marſhals</hi> wife of <hi>France</hi> ſaid to her husband at the ſtake, <hi>Be of good cheere, your wedding was but a ſhadow, an earneſt of the bleſſed marriage, which the Lambe will now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate.</hi> This then is the Marriage day of the godly, and who will not rejoyce, at leaſt a little with his friend on his Marriage day?</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18473:45"/>
                     <note place="margin">4. <hi>Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence.</hi>
                     </note>4. This is the day of their <hi>Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence,</hi> now their<note n="f" place="margin">Rev. 14.13.</note> 
                     <hi>workes follow them;</hi> now is their harveſt; though hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they have<note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 126.5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>ſowne in teares,</hi> yet now they <hi>reape in joy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. God gave our godly friends to us but for a ſeaſon, we are tenents at will, the Lord may put us out at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all our poſſeſſions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould learne with <hi>Iob</hi> to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our wills to Gods will, and ſay,<note n="h" place="margin">Job. 1.21.</note> 
                     <hi>the Lord gave, and the Lord taketh, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the name of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. We <hi>ſhall ſhortly</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 12 23.</note> 
                     <hi>goe to them,</hi> they cannot returne to us, it is but a little while, and we ſhall for ever have<note n="k" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4:13.14.17.</note> their fellowſhip in the Heavens.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. God will be inſtead of all, God will be to the widow, to the woman that hath no husband, inſtead of a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, to the fatherles child inſtead of a father, &amp;c. As <hi>Elka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hannah</hi> grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the barrennes of her wombe, becauſe ſhe had no children;<note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Why weepeſt thou? and why eateſt thou not? and why is thy heart grieved? am not I to thee better then ten ſonnes?</hi> So may I ſay in this behalfe, to every woman, every
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18473:45"/> child, every parent, every friend, why weepe ye? why eate ye not? why are your hearts grieved? Is not <hi>God</hi> to you in ſtead of ten husbands, ten children, ten friends? ſurely in <hi>God</hi> is all fulneſſe; and as the Sun is inſtead of all Candles, ſo ſhould the Lord be to us inſtead of all others, and infinitly more then all helpers, guides, ſtaies, friends, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters: Let then the thought of their advantage, who are gone the way of all fleſh before us, and the meditation of Gods conſtant, and never failing good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, mitigate the ſorrow, and ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which doth uſually attend our loſſe in this behalfe; let their gaine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwage the griefe of our loſſe, and alſo quicken us to a carefull preparation, that whenſoever the day of our diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſhall come, we may alſo have a fiery Charet with <hi>Eliah</hi> to carry us into the heavens.</p>
                  <p>Thus are we come to the laſt thing noted in <hi>Eliahs</hi> tranſlation, and aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: the <hi>inſtrumenta motus,</hi> the Angels of the Lord: whence obſerve; <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the holy Angels carry the ſoules of the righteous at the day of their death into
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18473:46"/> the heavens:</hi> they now<note n="m" place="margin">Pſa. 34.7</note> 
                     <hi>encampe about them,</hi> they now<note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 1.13</note> 
                     <hi>miniſter</hi> for their good, and at laſt will carry their ſoules to heaven, as they carried<note n="o" place="margin">Luke 16 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Lazarus</hi> into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome.</p>
                  <p>The ground of this their attendance upon the righteous, floweth from the Communion, and conjunction of Gods faithfull people with the Lord Jeſus; a woman joyned in wedlocke with the Prince, is honoured, reverenced, atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not onely by the common ſubjects, but alſo by the greateſt Nobles in that Princes Court; ſo the Spouſe of Chriſt, true believers, being married to Chriſt, are ſerved, attended, waited on, not onely by the common creatures, but alſo by the glorious Angels: O the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity whereunto man through Chriſt Jeſus is advanced! O that the Name of God might be magnified by us, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the honour he hath beſtowed upon us!</p>
                  <p>Thus from <hi>Eliahs</hi> Aſcenſion: let us deſcend unto, and looke upon <hi>Eliſhas</hi> Lamentation: wherein you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member was preſented to us a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold motive. The firſt externall: he ſaw
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18473:46"/> 
                     <hi>Eliah</hi> aſcending, and thereupon cryed. Wherein you may ſee; <hi>That the ſight of dying or departing is very forcible to move the affections of the ſurviving;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Lam. 3.51</note> 
                     <hi>mine eye affecteth my heart,</hi> was the ſaying of the Church in her <hi>Lamentations:</hi> but this I muſt now paſſe by.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond motive was his internall affection: <hi>My Father, my Father:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Note.</note> Where alſo learne; <hi>That Gods holy Miniſters are ſpirituall Fathers:</hi> and therefore they muſt be to Gods people, as fathers to the children; and muſt be loved, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, honoured by the people; as children love, reverence, honour them that be fathers over them.</p>
                  <p>The third motive was next;<note place="margin">Note.</note> drawne from the experience, <hi>Eliſha</hi> had of the ſafety, and defence miniſtred to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by the preſence of <hi>Eliah</hi> among them, therefore calling him <hi>the Horſemen of Iſrael, and the Charets thereof;</hi> becauſe as the <hi>horſemen</hi> and <hi>charets</hi> are the ſtrength of the people, and the inſtruments of their defence: ſo may we hereby learn; <hi>That Gods faithfull Miniſters are a ſingular ſtay and defence to the people where God hath ſet them:</hi> but becauſe time will not
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18473:47"/> give leave to ſpeak of theſe particulars, I will from the degree, increaſe, and ſigne of <hi>Eliſhas</hi> ſorrow, and from his affection, crying, renting his cloths, mourning as for a father, propoſe unto you this obſervation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
                     </label> 
                     <hi>That the death and departure of Gods faithfull Miniſters ought to be deeply &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately bewailed by Gods holy ſervants;</hi> as<note n="q" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.22.</note> 
                     <hi>David</hi> lamented, and all the people wept over <hi>Abner</hi> when he was ſlaine, being a great man in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a man that went forth to gather all <hi>Iſrael</hi> unto <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> ſo have we great cauſe to mourne for, and bewaile the death of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Captaines and Leaders, which are ſent forth to gather the people unto God, and to<note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18.19.</note> reconcile them, and bring them into Covenant with the <hi>Lord:</hi> thus <hi>Eliſha</hi> here bewailed the tranſlation of <hi>Eliah;</hi> and King <hi>Ioaſh</hi> afterwards in the ſame words lamenteth<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Kings 13, 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Eliſha.</hi> Now <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha</hi> was <hi>fallen ſicke of his ſickneſſe whereof he died, and Ioaſh King of Iſrael came down unto him, and wept over his face, and ſaid; O my father, my father, the Charets of Iſrael, and Horſmen thereof.</hi> And this is a part of the Churches lamentation,<note n="t" place="margin">Lam. 1.19 20.</note> 
                     <hi>My Prieſts
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18473:47"/> and mine Elders gave up the ghoſt in the Cty, behold O Lord, for I am in diſtreſſe:</hi> and this was a principall part of the peoples complaint, a great aggravation of their affliction,<note n="u" place="margin">Pſa. 74.9</note> 
                     <hi>We</hi> (ſay they) <hi>ſee not our ſignes, there is no more any Prophet, neither is there any among us that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how long:</hi> and when <hi>Paul</hi> departed from the people of <hi>God</hi> at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> this was their great griefe, that they ſhould ſee him no more, for at his departure from them it is recorded,<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 20.37, 38.</note> that <hi>he knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led downe, and prayed with them all, and they all wept ſore, and fell on Pauls necke, and kiſſed him, ſorrowing moſt of all for the words which he ſpake, that they ſhould ſee his face no more:</hi> and that the people of <hi>God</hi> ſhould thus deepely, thus affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately bewaile the death and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Gods Miniſters, there is great cauſe: for</p>
                  <p>Then they are without a <hi>Guide,</hi> as <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>1</label> children without a father to inſtruct, &amp; governe them; as a Ship without a Pilot to conduct them; as an Army without a Captaine to order them; as Sheepe without a Shepheard to lead them: ſo that as in the day of the King of <hi>Iſraels</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18473:48"/> fall, the Prophet <hi>in viſion,</hi> ſaw the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſcattered like ſheep without a<note n="x" place="margin">1 King. 22 17.</note> ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, and as men having no maſter: So when the faithfull Miniſter of God, the ſpirituall Paſtor is taken away, then are the <hi>people ſcattered abroad,</hi> as<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 9 36</note> 
                     <hi>ſheep having no ſhepheard;</hi> then they are as travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers without a guid: then they are as the <hi>Syrians,</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">2 Kings 6 18, 19.</note> that had their eyes put out, &amp; went they knew not whither, into their enemies City, when they thought they had beene travelling to their owne Countrey; ſo people, when the faithfull Miniſters of the Goſpell are taken from them, they be as men without eyes, they thinke they are in a good, when they are in a very evill eſtate; in the way to life, when they be in the very gates of death; for the Miniſters are the eyes of the people, therefore called<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 30.10</note> 
                     <hi>Seers;</hi> and as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid to <hi>Hobab,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Numbers.</note> 
                     <hi>Leave us not I pray thee, for as much as we are to encamp in the wilderneſſe, and thou mayeſt be inſtead of eyes to us;</hi> ſo may the people ſay to the Miniſter of God, <hi>Leave us not we beſeech thee, for as much as we are to travell thorow the Wilderneſſe of this World, and thou maiſt be to us inſtead of eyes:</hi> in ſtead of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18473:48"/> eyes to teach us to diſcerne the things which differ, to foreſee evils to come, to ſhew us the myſteries of ſalvation, to guide us into the wayes of peace; &amp; therefore as it would grieve a man to have his eyes put out, ſo it ſhould much grieve us to have the Miniſters of God, our ſpirituall eyes, taken from us.</p>
                  <p>Then they are without ſpirituall food, as children that have loſt their Father, their Mother, their nurſe, are often without bodily food; for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God are their ſpirituall<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.16.</note> 
                     <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> the<note n="c" place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Nurſes</hi> which muſt draw forth the breaſts of ſpirituall conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to nouriſh them, the <hi>ſhepheards</hi> which muſt<note n="d" place="margin">Jer. 3.15. Joh. 21.16.17.</note> 
                     <hi>feede</hi> them with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding, the<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 13.52.</note> 
                     <hi>ſtewards</hi> which muſt bring forth <hi>old and new out of their treaſury,</hi> which muſt open and apply both the Law and the Goſpell to their conſcience:<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1.</note> 
                     <hi>faithfull ſtewards,</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> 
                     <hi>dividing the word aright, giving every one his portion, and that in due ſeaſon.</hi> Without theſe there is a ſpirituall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, a famine not of bread and water, but which is farre worſe, a<note n="h" place="margin">Amos 8.11.</note> 
                     <hi>famine of hearing the word of the Lord.</hi> Without
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18473:49"/> theſe the people at the beſt are but like the ſheepe brought by <hi>Labans</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the well, but could not drinke, till <hi>Iacob rolled away the</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 29 8 10.</note> 
                     <hi>ſtone;</hi> for what elſe doth an un-teaching Miniſter, but gather the people to the well, call them to the word, to heare the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but are unable to roll away the ſtone, to give the<note n="k" place="margin">Neh. 8.8</note> 
                     <hi>ſence</hi> as <hi>Ezra</hi> did, to divide the word, and give them waters out of the wells of life: and therefore as it would much trouble us to bee in a bodily, ſo ſhould it much more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet us to bee under a ſpirituall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>3</label> Then they be without their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all comforter, as children when their parents are gone, then their Comforter is gone: the faithfull Miniſters are the Comforters of <hi>Sion,</hi> theſe have the charge given to miniſter conſolation to the people;<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 40.1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>comfort yee, comfort yee my people,</hi> (ſaith our God) <hi>ſpeake yee comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably to Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>ſonnes of</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 4.36</note> 
                     <hi>Conſolation,</hi> theſe are the <hi>Doves</hi> which bring the <hi>Olive branch</hi> of peace to the ſoule in the deluge of trouble: their voyce through Gods
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18473:49"/> bleſſing doth appeaſe the troubled conſcience, as the<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 8.25 26.</note> 
                     <hi>voyce</hi> of our <hi>Saviour</hi> appeaſed the ſtormy tempeſt: theſe under God are the Phyſitians which heale our wounded ſoules, when all the World cannot cure us, nor miniſter any peace or comfort to us, as our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> cured the<note n="o" place="margin">Mark. 5.39.</note> 
                     <hi>woman of her bloudy iſſue, after that ſhee had ſpent all that ſhe had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Phyſitians, and yet was not healed:</hi> for theſe are the men to whom God hath given the<note n="p" place="margin">Iſa. 5.40.</note> 
                     <hi>tongue of the learned, to miniſter a word in due ſeaſon;</hi> when theſe therefore are gone, the Inſtruments of our comfort are gone, our ſtarre is ſet, we are left in darkeneſſe, and are as the Church when ſhe had no <hi>Comforter. Lament.</hi> 1.9.<note n="q" place="margin">Lam. 1.19.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then they are without the meanes <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>4</label> of their ſpirituall freedom, eaſily taken and kept in the bondage of <hi>Satan;</hi> when the Parents are gone, ſtrangers uſe to make a pray of the children; ſo when the Miniſters of God are taken away, when the ſpirituall Parents are removed, then ſin, Satan, and the world eaſily make a pray of the people; for the faithfull Miniſtry of the Goſpell is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18473:50"/> the thunder by which the divell muſt be caſt down to the ground like<note n="r" place="margin">Luke 10.18.</note> 
                     <hi>light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> this is the warlike weapon which is mighty thorough God to <hi>caſt downe the ſtrong</hi>
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Cor. 10 4.5.</note> 
                     <hi>holds of ſinne;</hi> as the walles of<note n="t" place="margin">Joſ. 6.20.</note> 
                     <hi>Ierico</hi> were throwne downe by the ſounding of the <hi>Rammes hornes,</hi> ſo the walles of ſinne, the ſtrong holds of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan are overturned by ſounding forth the trumpet of the Goſpell. Before <hi>Philip</hi> came to <hi>Samaria,</hi> Satan had the poſſeſſion there, but when he came and preached the Goſpell, then the<note n="u" place="margin">Acts 8.8 9.</note> 
                     <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirits</hi> went out of many that were poſſeſſed with them; thus is the Miniſtry of the word an inſtrument of victory to Gods people over the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of their ſalvation: but when the Miniſtry faileth, then Satans Kingdome is erected, then his throne flouriſheth; when the gardener is taken away, then the garden becommeth a wilderneſſe; when the ſhepheard is gone, the flocke is ſcatered, the wild beaſt maketh a pray of it; as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe,<note n="w" place="margin">Pſal. 104 20, 21.</note> 
                     <hi>the Lord maketh darkeneſſe, &amp; it is night, wherein all the beaſts of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt doe creepe forth, and the Lyons roare
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18473:50"/> after their prey;</hi> ſo here when the <hi>Lord</hi> taketh away the light of the Goſpell, bringeth darkneſſe, a ſpirituall night upon us, then ſinne, and ſatan the<note n="x" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8</note> 
                     <hi>roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lyon</hi> creepe forth, then they make a prey of the ſoules of men, then they fill them full of all uncleanneſſe, then the faithfull City becommeth an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, a denne of darkneſſe, a lodge of all uncleanneſſe: behold this in the Churches, once eminent, &amp; famous for their knowledge, faith, and holineſſe, but now very ſinkes of ſinne, and all abominations.</p>
                  <p>Then they are without their defence, <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>5</label> as a child when the father is dead, when the parents are gone, is in a ſort with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Protectour; as a flocke without a ſhepheard, lyeth open to the mouth of every Dog, Fox, Beare, Lyon, Theefe: therefore are the Miniſters ſtiled, the <hi>Horſemen</hi> and <hi>Charets of Iſrael,</hi> becauſe they are the ſtrength and ſafegard of the place where they are: where the word of God is purely and ſincerely taught, there <hi>God</hi> is after a peculiar manner preſent, ſhewing his power in the defence of the place and people: to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18473:51"/> the Miniſter of <hi>God</hi> hath made a very gracious promiſe,<note n="y" place="margin">Ier. 1.18, 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Lord</hi> to <hi>Jeremy) I have made thee this day a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenced City, and an iron Pillar, and braſen wall againſt the whole Land, againſt the Kings of Judah, againſt the Princes thereof, againſt the Prieſts thereof, and againſt the people of the Land: And they ſhall fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, but they ſhal not prevaile againſt thee, for I am with thee to deliver thee.</hi> And the <hi>Lord</hi> is not onely a defence to the Miniſters themſelves, but alſo to the place and people where they are; thus when the <hi>Syrians</hi> compaſſed the City <hi>Dothan</hi> where <hi>Eliſha</hi> was, then were the <hi>mountaines full of Charets and Horſes, the Angels of the Lord like an Army ſtanding in the defence of Eliſha,</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">2 Kings 6 16, 17.</note> ſo that the <hi>Syrians</hi> could hurt neither <hi>Eliſha</hi> nor the place where he was: thus alſo when the<note n="a" place="margin">2 Chro. 11.13, 14, 16, 17.</note> 
                     <hi>Prieſts, the Levites, and ſuch of the Tribes of Iſrael, as ſet their hearts to ſeeke the Lord God of Iſrael, came to Jeruſalem, then they ſtrengthned the Kingdome of Iudah, and made Rehoboam ſtrong, even ſo many yeares as he wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the waies of David and Salomon.</hi> It is not ſo much the number of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18473:51"/> people, the great abundance of riches, and other munition and furniture, as holy and faithfull Miniſters, pious and religious people, that are the ſtrength, ſtay, &amp; inſtruments of ſafety to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, place or people: therefore when <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> ſent forth them that taught in <hi>Iudah,</hi> and had the booke of the Law of the <hi>Lord</hi> with them, and went about throughout all the Cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and taught the people; then it is ſaid,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Chro. 17.9.</note> 
                     <hi>the feare of the Lord fell upon all the Kingdoms of the Lands that were round about Iudah, ſo that they made no war againſt Iehoſaphat:</hi> yea they did not onely forbeare to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy and hurt him, but then alſo the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> brought <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> preſents, and tribute ſilver, and the <hi>Arabians</hi> brought him flockes, ſeven thouſand and ſeven hundred <hi>Rammes,</hi> and ſeven thouſand and ſeven hundred <hi>He-goats:</hi> behold here the bleſſed ſafety, the great defence miniſtred to the place &amp; peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, where the <hi>Lord</hi> giveth faithfull and teaching Miniſters to inſtruct them: ſee and conſider in this, the ſingular good attendant upon, and derived unto the places which the Lord endowes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18473:52"/> with ſanctified and able Paſtors; they by their labours convert many to true holineſſe, fill the ſoules of many with much goodneſſe, make them very fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the good workes of all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, bring them to be <hi>Gods</hi> deare favourites; they by their prayers alſo previle with <hi>God</hi> for the removall of much evill hanging over, and for the procuring of much good to the place and people where the <hi>Lord</hi> doth ſet them: and thus they are inſtrumentally a ſingular defence unto them, but theſe being removed, the people become like a City having neither wall nor watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>6</label> Then they are without their honour, for as the Parents be in ſome ſort the honour of the children, as well as the children be the crowne of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; ſo are the Miniſters and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>God</hi> the crowne and glory of the people, which enjoy them: therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> tels <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>there was no Nation ſo</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 4.6</note> 
                     <hi>great as they, becauſe there was no Nation had God ſo nigh unto them, that had ſuch ſtatutes as they, and this was their wiſdome and underſtanding to keepe them:</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18473:52"/> therefore alſo when the <hi>Ark,</hi> which was to <hi>Iſrael</hi> a teſtimony of <hi>Gods</hi> preſence, as the Ordinances of <hi>God</hi> are now to us, when this <hi>Arke</hi> I ſay was taken from them, the wife of <hi>Phineas</hi> refuſed to be comforted, ſaying, the<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 4.21, 22.</note> 
                     <hi>glory was departed from Iſrael:</hi> for as the ſtars be the glory and ornament of the heavens, ſo are the Miniſters of <hi>God</hi> the<note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 1.19</note> 
                     <hi>ſtarres</hi> in the right hand of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the ornaments and glory of the Church: a great priviledge, a rare favour are <hi>Gods</hi> ordinances where he doth vouchſafe them:<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 147 19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſheweth his word</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt) unto Iacob, his ſtatutes and his judgements unto Iſrael: he hath not dealt ſo with any Nation, and as for his judgements, they have not known them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then they are in great danger of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> was but a few daies <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>7</label> abſent from the people, they erected a<note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 32 1, 2.</note> 
                     <hi>golden calfe</hi> to goe before them: when <hi>Iehoaida</hi> dyed,<note n="h" place="margin">2 Chr. 24.2, 17, 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Iehoaſh</hi> ſoon turned aſide from the way of <hi>God</hi> to Idols, the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers will ſoone go backe, if their Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der be once gone; the ſhip will quickly miſcarry, make ſhipwracke, if there be no Pilot in it.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18473:53"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons </seg>8</label> Laſtly then, they are, in a manner without religion, without piety, yea without God and Chriſt in the world: when the people were without the Law, and a teaching Prieſt, they were ſaid to be<note n="i" place="margin">2 Chro, 15.2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>without God.</hi> The taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way then of the faithfull Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſſe then a depriving of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of their guides, food, comforters, meanes of ſpirituall freedome, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of defence, this robbing them of their glory, expoſing them to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Apoſtacy, and making them like men without God in the World, we cannot but confeſſe that the death and departure of Gods faithfull. Miniſters ought to be deepely and affectionately bewailed by Gods holy ſervants.</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
                     </label> This therefore ſerveth for the juſt and ſharpe reproofe of all ſuch as doe not heartily, feelingly, and affectiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely bewaile the departure, death, and want of Gods faithful miniſters, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of theſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dleſticks, the going out of theſe bright and ſhining lights: many of us now are like <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, weary of our heavenly <hi>Manna,</hi> as they of<note n="k" place="margin">Num. 11.56.</note> 
                     <hi>theirs,</hi> and as they <hi>fell a luſting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18473:53"/> after the onions, and fleſh pots of Egypt'</hi> ſo doe many of us after the old <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> doctrine, though the Goſpel was never taught amongſt us, opened to us with ſuch cleareneſſe, power, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and demonſtration of the ſpirit as now, yet becauſe it hath been long continued, many begin to loath it, to grow very weary of it, to take, at leaſt, no pleaſure in it. It was <hi>Seneca</hi> his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of old, <hi>Sol ſpectatorem non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, niſi cum deficit, nemo obſervat Lu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nam, niſi laborantem, adeò naturale eſt magis nova quàm magna mirari; the Sunne hath no beholder except eclipſed, no man obſerveth the Moone, unleſſe when ſhe is in travell; ſo naturall it is unto us to admire new things, rather then great things:</hi> The doctrine which is ſtiled Popiſh we reject, becauſe it hath an old name, but let the ſame doctrine come under a new name, a doctrine as like the Popiſh, as one egge is like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as the Sunne that ſhines now, is like that which ſhined many yeeres agoe; or rather if yee will, as the bramble which groweth now, is like
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18473:54"/> the bramble which grew a hundred yeeres ſince; though a man might ſay to the teachers and embracers of it; as the Prophet to <hi>Jeroboams</hi> wife diſguiſing her ſelfe,<note n="l" place="margin">1 King. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>come in, come in, thou wife of</hi> Jeroboam, <hi>why faineſt thou thy ſelfe to be another then thou art?</hi> So we in this caſe, for as ſhe was the ſame woman, onely her apparell and geſture was changed, ſo let this be the ſame doctrine with that which we call Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, yet becauſe under a new name, a little diſguiſed, ſomewhat arrayed in another apparell, it will be by ſome highly eſteemed, ſtrongly imbraced, the fall of truth and faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God not at all bewailed: and what doe men by this declare, but that 1. They were never of<note n="m" place="margin">Ioh. 18.37 Ioh. 2.19.</note> 
                     <hi>the truth.</hi> 2. That they never unfainedly<note n="n" place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.10</note> 
                     <hi>loved</hi> the truth. 3. That they never<note n="o" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2, 3</note> 
                     <hi>felt</hi> the <hi>ſaving power</hi> nor heavenly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of it, if they had taſted the ſweetneſſe of it, been acquainted with the joy and peace which this mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth, had they ſeene the beauties, the glory and excellency of God in it, then
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18473:54"/> as <hi>Peter</hi> beholding the glorious trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuration of our Saviour, ſaid,<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 17.4.</note> 
                     <hi>It is good being here, let us build three Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, &amp;c.</hi> ſo would they ſay, it is good being under the Goſpel, it is pleaſant, it is comfortable being here, let us build our Tabernacle here, O let us dwell under this forever.</p>
                  <p>This muſt therefore move us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the loſſe of Gods faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, the removing of theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable and ſhining Candleſticks; as the childe bewaileth the loſſe of his parent, the Traveller the loſſe of his Guide, the Patient the death of his Phyſitian, the Army the fall of their Generall; and as all <hi>Iſrael</hi> was gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, and<note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 25.1</note> 
                     <hi>lamented</hi> the death of their <hi>Samuel:</hi> ſo have you great cauſe to lament the death of your <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> the departure of your faithfull Paſtor: As <hi>Ionah</hi> was much grieved at the<note n="q" place="margin">Ionah 4.6, 7, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>withering</hi> of the <hi>Gourd,</hi> which was a ſhadow over his head, a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table protection and refreſhment to him, ſo have you great occaſion to be grieved much at his withering, at his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18473:55"/> diſſolution, who was a ſhadow, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of much, of ſweet refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (whiles he lived) to your ſoules. And as <hi>Hagar</hi> ſate downe and<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 21.16.</note> 
                     <hi>wept</hi> becauſe her <hi>bottle was empty,</hi> ſo have you great cauſe now to ſit downe and weepe, becauſe the well which was wont to ſend forth waters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, is now dryed up: for now you may behold how your <hi>Eliah,</hi> like him of old, though not in body, yet in ſoule is gone in his <hi>Fiery Charet</hi> into Heaven; he who ſhined like the Sun to you of this place for ſome yeeres, is now gone downe from your Horizon, whom your eyes ſhall ſee no more till the morning of the <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 13.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Tree</hi> whoſe fruit lately fed you, whoſe branches lately ſhadowed and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you, is now withered, dead and dry, no more fruit to bee gathered from him: he that was in ſome reſpect the <hi>Father, the Charets and Horſemen</hi> of this place, is now like <hi>Eliah</hi> parted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder from you; he that ſtood like<note n="t" place="margin">Ge. 29.8, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Jacob, to roll away the ſtone from the Well,</hi> to open and give you the ſence
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18473:55"/> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> can now no more doe that office for you: He that lately ſtood like a<note n="u" place="margin">Iſa. 60.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Watchman</hi> upon your walles, to awaken you, to warne you, is now by death put to ſilence, and can no more call upon you: hee who of late like a good Steward brought out of his ſtore-houſe old and new, brake the bread of life amongſt you, hath now given account of his ſtewardſhip, and ſhall no more bee ſteward over you. God gave you a great bleſſing in him, the Lord grant there be no curſe attend his removall. Sure I am as the people ſaid of <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note n="w" place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note> 
                     <hi>thou art worth ten thouſand of us;</hi> ſo may we ſay of him, he was worth a great number of them that doe ſurvive him: the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was his worth, the more ſhould be your griefe, yet as our Saviour ſaid to the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 23.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Jeruſalem weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves and for your children;</hi> ſo may I ſay to you, weep not for him that is now departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, but weep for your ſelves &amp; for your children, for the great loſſe you have taken; as for the gaine which hee hath gotten, the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18473:56"/> crowne which he hath won, there is cauſe of rejoycing: for hee you well know, was a man in whom there was a rare confluence of all vertues, as of lines meeting in one Center, ſtreames running into one Ocean; there was indeed a ſingular compleatneſſe in him, his ſoule was a rich ſtore-houſe, a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious garden, having jewels and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of all ſorts, a Tree laden with all kind of fruits: I may ſay of him as <hi>Horace</hi> in another caſe, —<hi>Micat inter omnes Iulium ſydus, velut inter ignes Luna minores:</hi> and as the people ſaid of<note n="y" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Saul</hi> in regard of his endowments, <hi>He was the head and ſhoulders above ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others:</hi> For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Lord enriched him with much knowledge, according to the propheſie hee was filled with this, as the Sea with<note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 11.6</note> 
                     <hi>waters,</hi> his Lampe was full of this oyle; hee was as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaid of the <hi>Baptiſt, a bright and ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Iohn. 5.35.</note> 
                     <hi>light,</hi> the Lord gave him the tongue of the <hi>learned to miniſter a word in</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 50.4.</note> 
                     <hi>due ſeaſon.</hi> 2. The Lord repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed him with ſuch a rare dexterity,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18473:56"/> ſingular wiſdome, to diſcerne, adviſe, and give counſell fit for every eſtate and undertaking: of whom I may ſay in this behalfe, as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 40.38, 39</note> 
                     <hi>Ioſeph, Can we finde ſuch a man as this was, a man in whom the ſpirit of</hi> God <hi>was;</hi> ſurely there are few ſo diſcreet and wiſe as he was. 3. He was diligent and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in his calling, a good Steward, ever breaking the bread of life amongſt you, a loving Nurſe alwayes drawing forth his breaſt unto you; he was not a cloud without raine, a Well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water, he did not hide his talent in a napkin; hee did not put his light under a buſhell; but as the Sun doth often viſit the earth, ſo did hee this place: as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Macedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in regard of their contribution to the Saints, <hi>to</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3.</note> 
                     <hi>their power, and beyond their power they were willing:</hi> ſo this man in his calling was willing to his power, and as ſome conjecture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his power in regard of his bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infirmities. 4. He was not onely diligent in his calling, but alſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in his teaching, it was not<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 23.28</note> 
                     <hi>chaffe,</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:18473:57"/> but good <hi>wheat</hi> which hee ſowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, not the ſand of humane devices, but the firme and ſure Rocke of Gods Word, did he lay as a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for you thereon to build; hee ſought not with humane eloquence, vaine flaſhes, idle quirks, phantaſticall conceits, and<note n="f" place="margin">1 Cor. 8.3.</note> 
                     <hi>inticing words of mans wiſedome</hi> to pleaſe men, but his labour was to ſpeake and preach <hi>in the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit and of power; that your faith might not ſtand in the wiſdome of men, but in the power of God:</hi> and this indeed is not the leaſt part both of the wiſdome and fidelity required of Gods meſſengers to ſtoop to the capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of the people, to preſent the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God plainely to their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. <hi>Bonorum ingeniorum eſt inſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis indoles</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) in verbis verum amare, non verba: quid enim prodeſt clavis aurea ſi aperire quod volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus non poteſt, aut quid obeſt-lignea, ſi hoc poteſt, quando nihil aliud quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus niſi ut pateat quod clauſum eſt?</hi> This is a ſingular property of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in words to love the truth, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18473:57"/> not the words: what doth a golden key profit if it cannot open what we would have unſhut; what doth a wooden key hurt or hinder, if it can open, when as wee deſire no more but that which is ſhut may be opened, that which is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den may be unfolded? he is ſurely in <hi>Gods</hi> ſchoole the beſt ſcholler in <hi>Gods</hi> Church the moſt eminent and worthy teacher, that doth with moſt cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, plaineneſſe, power, fulneſſe and evidence of the ſpirit open and apply <hi>Gods</hi> counſels to the conſciences of the hearers. 5. He was alſo in his diſcourſe very holy, and profitable, a ſeeds-man alwaies ſowing, a light alwaies ſhining, very conſtant in doing good by his communication. 6. Hee was in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of his converſation very ſincere and upright, ſo farre as ever I obſerved, and I am perſwaded it was the joy and<note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note> rejoycing of his heart, that he had his converſation in ſincerity and upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not in fleſhly wiſedome. 7. Hee was very friendly to Gods people, with them hee delighted to converſe, Gods image, true goodneſſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18473:58"/> in them, was a load-ſtone very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to move and draw his affection. 8. He was open-handed to ſuch as nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ready out of his fulneſſe to powre plentifully into ſuch veſſels as hee found empty. 9. By his converſation he gave a good example, hee did not build with one hand and pull downe with the other, but his doctrine and his converſation were at a ſweet agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, like <hi>Ruth</hi> and <hi>Naomi</hi> they went hand in hand together. 10. He was not one in publike, another in private, but every where the ſame; as they ſaid of <hi>Valerins</hi> Court, ſo may wee ſay of his houſe, it was a Church of God in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded of the holy orders orderly there obſerved, and religious duties there performed. Now therefore walke ye in that light which hee hath cauſed to ſhine unto you, bring forth the fruit of that ſeede which he hath ſown among you, and build up that ſacred and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving truth which hee hath propoſed and ſet before you. And now laſtly;</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If the death, departure, &amp; loſſe of <hi>Gods</hi> faithfull Miniſters bee ſo deeply to be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18473:58"/> bewailed, if our eſtate without them be ſo wretched, ſo uncomfortable; then you muſt ſhew your ſelves very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in repairing the loſſe which you have now ſuſtained, doe not ye ſay as <hi>Galienus</hi> the Emperor when hee had loſt <hi>Aegypt, cannot wee bee without the hempe and flaxe of Aegypt;</hi> and when he had alſo loſt <hi>France,</hi> two great and mighty Countries, <hi>cannot the Lord</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>ſtand ſine ſagis trabeatis, without theſe ſouldiers caſſockes which</hi> France <hi>doth ſend us. Beloved,</hi> I beſeech you do not ſo ſay of the departure of Gods Miniſters, doe not ſlight the loſſe of them, as if it were but the loſſe of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle flaxe, hempe, or a few ſouldiers coates; but looke upon it I intreate you, and conſider it, and be affected with it, as with one of the greateſt loſſes could ever be ſuſtained, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly declare and ſhew your wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, circumſpection, care diligence, faithfulneſſe, and conſcionableneſſe for an able ſupply. And for your better direction in this behalfe, let it be your care.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:18473:59"/>1. To goe to <hi>God,</hi> and by prayer &amp; faſting ſeeke his counſell and aſſiſtance, as the people in the dayes of <hi>Ezra</hi> by<note n="h" place="margin">Ezra 8.21.</note> 
                     <hi>prayer and faſting</hi> ſought of <hi>God</hi> a way for them and their little ones; ſo doe you now by prayer and faſting ſeeke of <hi>God</hi> an able and faithfull Miniſter, to guide both you and your little ones in the way that leadeth to peace and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſſe. As the people after the death of<note n="i" place="margin">Jud. 1.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ioſhua, went to God and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him, who ſhould goe up for them to fight againſt the Canaanites,</hi> ſo muſt you now after the death of your ſpirituall Leader, goe to <hi>God,</hi> and aske of him, who ſhall goe up for you to fight for you in this warre againſt ſinne and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan: this is not more holineſſe then is requiſite, for thus the Diſciples ſought to <hi>God</hi> by<note n="k" place="margin">Act 1.24</note> 
                     <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>faſting,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them in the choice of a ſucceſſour in the roome of him that fell.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Seeke not too much to pleaſe your ſelves, be not too indulgent to your owne affections, but let your ſpeciall ayme be at the glory of <hi>God,</hi> and the generall and ſaving good of the people
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18473:59"/> of this place: let that man which in all probability, and upon good evidence will be moſt zealous for <hi>Gods</hi> glory, and doe beſt ſervice to the people of this place, be without any by or ſiniſter reſpect the man of your choice. This doe, or elſe for any thing I know <hi>God</hi> may require the bloud of this people at your hands.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Bee carefull that the man whom you chooſe be <hi>a man after Gods owne</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">h</hi> 
                     <hi>heart,</hi> a holy man, a man able to feed you with knowlege and underſtanding, a man experienced in the worke of <hi>Gods word</hi> upon his owne ſoule: for as <hi>Christ was made like unto us in allm</hi> 
                     <hi>things ſin excepted, that he might have compaſsion on us in all our eſtates and conditions;</hi> ſo it is requiſite the Miniſter of <hi>God</hi> ſhould be made like the people in all things, I meane in being ſenſible of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſinne, of the trouble of an affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted conſcience, of the buffetings of Satan, of the worke of <hi>Gods word</hi> and ſpirit upon his owne heart: and then ſhall he be fit to compaſſionate, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, teach the people, and know how to <hi>miniſter a word in due ſeaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:18473:60"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. Remember that of the <hi>Lord</hi> to <hi>Samuell,</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">1 Sa. 16.7.</note> 
                     <hi>judge not after the outward appearance;</hi> and take this for a ſure rule, that God doth not alwayes doe the greateſt works by men of greateſt earth-abilities: the <hi>Lord</hi> over-turned the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianitiſh</hi> hoaſt by a<note n="o" place="margin">Jud. 7.23</note> 
                     <hi>barley cake,</hi> by<note n="p" place="margin">Judg. 6.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Gedion whoſe family was poore in</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh <hi>and that was the liaſt in his fathers houſe:</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> cauſed the<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 17 6</note> 
                     <hi>waters</hi> to come forth out of the <hi>rocke,</hi> by no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, no worthier inſtrument, then the ſtroke of a <hi>rod.</hi> It was not in <hi>Sauls</hi> armour, but with a<note n="r" place="margin">1 Sa. 17.54.</note> 
                     <hi>ſling</hi> and a <hi>ſtone</hi> that God enabled <hi>David</hi> to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw <hi>Goliah,</hi> and delever <hi>Iſrael.</hi> They were Trumpets neither of gold nor ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ioſ. 6.20</note> 
                     <hi>rams hornes,</hi> contemptible things in the eyes of men, which God cauſed the Prieſt to ſound, and at whoſe ſounding the walles of <hi>Iericho</hi> fell. And the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> telleth us, that God <hi>hath ordained ſtrength out of the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 8.2.</note> 
                     <hi>mouthes of babes, and ſucklings:</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> layeth it downe as a generall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant rule, <hi>the</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26, 27, 28, 29.</note> 
                     <hi>fooliſhneſſe of</hi> God <hi>is vvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then men,</hi> and the <hi>weakeneſſe of</hi> God
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18473:60"/> 
                     <hi>is ſtronger then men:</hi> for yee ſee your calling brethren, how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble men are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but God <hi>hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wife:</hi> and God <hi>hath choſen the weake things of the world, to confound the things which are mighty; and baſe things of the world, and things which are deſpiſed hath</hi> God <hi>choſen; yea and things which are not, to bring to nought things which are:</hi> and he rendreth the reaſon of the <hi>Lords</hi> ſo doing, that <hi>no fleſh ſhould glory in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:</hi> Thinke on theſe things, and <hi>be not wiſe in your owne eyes;</hi> this have I ſpoken not as vnder-valuing abilities humane, but as adviſing that you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten not your eyes too much upon them, leaſt they prove a ſandy founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And as for him that ſhall ſucceed your now deceaſed Paſtor, my prayer is, that as the ſpirit of <hi>Eliah</hi> was doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon <hi>Eliſha,</hi> ſo the ſpirit of this man may be doubled on him that ſhall in this place ſucceed him, that hee may prove to you as a bright and a ſhining
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18473:61"/> ſtarre to leade you, as the ſtarre led the wiſe men to <hi>Chriſt Ieſus;</hi> and as the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pillar conducted <hi>Iſrael</hi> form <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan,</hi> ſo may he lead you from the <hi>Egypt</hi> of ſinne, and bondage of Satan, to the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> that place of glory, reſt, peace, and all fulneſſe, which God hath provided for his children in the holy and higeſt heavens.</p>
                  <closer>Laus Deo ſoli.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18473:61"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
